<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breviate of the proceedings of France, from the Pyrenaean Treaty to this time as also I. The speech of Monsieur Zierowsky, the Emperor's Embassador to the King of Poland, II. A memorial presented by the said Embassador to the King of Poland, III. A letter from Monsieur Du Vernay to Count Tekeley, IV. A letter from Count Tekeley to Monsieur Du Vernay, V. A letter from Monsieur Peter Jaigel, Governour of Cassovia, to Monsieur De Vernay.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12124873</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12124873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29339)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 759:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breviate of the proceedings of France, from the Pyrenaean Treaty to this time as also I. The speech of Monsieur Zierowsky, the Emperor's Embassador to the King of Poland, II. A memorial presented by the said Embassador to the King of Poland, III. A letter from Monsieur Du Vernay to Count Tekeley, IV. A letter from Count Tekeley to Monsieur Du Vernay, V. A letter from Monsieur Peter Jaigel, Governour of Cassovia, to Monsieur De Vernay.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 185 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Cologne, and reprinted at London, to be sold by Walter Davies ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54547:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54547:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BREVIATE OF THE <hi>Proceedings</hi> OF FRANCE, From the <hi>PYRENAEAN TREATY</hi> to this <hi>TIME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO,
<list>
                  <item>I. The Speech of Monſieur <hi>Zierowsky,</hi> the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi>'s Embaſſador to the <hi>King</hi> of POLAND.</item>
                  <item>II. A Memorial preſented by the ſaid Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to the King of POLAND.</item>
                  <item>III. A <hi>Letter</hi> from Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to Count <hi>Tekeley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. A <hi>Letter</hi> from Count <hi>Tekeley</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. A <hi>Letter</hi> from Monſieur <hi>Peter Jaigel,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Cologne,</hi> and Reprinted at <hi>London,</hi> to be ſold by <hi>Walter Davies</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54547:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54547:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Author</hi> of this <hi>Little Diſcourſe</hi> was moſt certainly a <hi>French Proteſtant,</hi> and One who has been a <hi>Sufferer</hi> among the <hi>Reſt</hi> in the late <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> 'Tis but a <hi>ſmall Treatiſe,</hi> but it gives the <hi>World</hi> a <hi>large Proſpect</hi> of the <hi>Violencies</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> of the <hi>French Government,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:54547:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad;</hi> and the <hi>Miſeries</hi> of thoſe that lye under it's <hi>Oppreſſion.</hi> How far it may have an <hi>Influence</hi> upon Other <hi>Nations,</hi> or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the <hi>Author's Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> who has made it his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to exhort them to the <hi>Recovery</hi> of their <hi>Liberty,</hi> wreſted from them by <hi>Bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Breach</hi> of <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Correſpondence</hi> with the <hi>Turks</hi> Themſelves, to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> of ſo many <hi>Families</hi> as have periſhed in the <hi>Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of their <hi>Country</hi> and the Ruin of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it
<pb facs="tcp:54547:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelf, I know not; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to our <hi>own,</hi> it may be of <hi>Great Advantage,</hi> to make the <hi>People</hi> conſider the <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities</hi> they enjoy under a <hi>King truly Moſt Chriſtian,</hi> a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>peaceable Soveraign,</hi> and how much more happy they are than their <hi>Neighbours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and how industriouſly they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to bring Themſelves into the ſame <hi>Condition</hi> by their own <hi>needleſs Diſcontents</hi> and <hi>Fiery Diſſentions:</hi> Which certainly they would never do, did they but ſeriouſly weigh in the ſame <hi>Ballance</hi> the <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:54547:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Dominion</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> hereafter diſplayed, and the <hi>Immunities</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> we Enjoy by the <hi>Excellent Compoſure</hi> of our <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> both <hi>in Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="France" type="history">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54547:4"/>
               <head>THE AMBITION OF FRANCE UPON EUROPE.</head>
               <p>IT is no difficult thing to diſcern the Original of thoſe Miſeries under which we labour at this day: They who will give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Trouble to reflect upon the Tranſactions, which have been the moſt remarkable for theſe <hi>Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> years laſt paſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> will agree with me, that if we had been ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54547:5"/> to have <hi>grown wife by our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> we ſhould not have ſeen our ſelves reduc'd to thoſe <hi>Calamities</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we now groan. For in ſhort this is not the firſt time, that <hi>France</hi> has been known to have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Leagues, tho never ſo ſacred and inviolable. Her Ambition has not been able to keep her ſelf reſerv'd without appearing in her <hi>Colours.</hi> But we have been either ſo weak or ſo blind, as never to make a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous oppoſition till it was too late. Therefore we can only impute our <hi>Misfortunes</hi> to our ſelves, and muſt ingeniouſly confeſs, that if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at this day the puniſhment of our <hi>Imprudence,</hi> 'tis no more than what we juſtly deſerve.</p>
               <p>In a word, to whom ought we to impute the <hi>Imbecillity</hi> of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54547:5"/> but to our ſelves, who have ſo often contributed to reduce them to their preſent condition? Was it not eaſy for us to ſee, that they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported themſelves only by the <hi>means</hi> of thoſe <hi>Cabals,</hi> that were maintain'd in <hi>France</hi> againſt Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> and that if the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> had forſaken their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> their good <hi>Fortune</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> had been at an end? nevertheleſs when we obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that we had loſt the Aſſiſtance of that Prince, who was return'd to his Duty by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace, and that <hi>France</hi> to the prejudice of a League ſo ſacredly ratify'd, forbore not however, not only to foment the <hi>Troubles</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> but alſo to ſend conſiderable Supplys to their aſſiſtance at ſeveral times; I ſay, when we ſaw, that the <hi>Peace</hi> was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54547:6"/> no more than a Cloak for <hi>France</hi>'s Ambition, have we not ſuffer'd the Oppreſſion of our Neighbours, without ſo much as opening our Lips, as if <hi>True Policy</hi> had not taught us, that it was time to oppoſe the <hi>Deſigns</hi> of a <hi>Nation,</hi> which would never be contented, 'till ſhe had ſatisfy'd her <hi>Ambition</hi> by the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of the World?</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, with what confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, if I may not call it Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, did ſhe maintain, that ſhe acted nothing but what was confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Peace? Did not ſhe likewiſe inſinuate, that whatever was done in the behalf of <hi>Portugal,</hi> was done without her Order? To which purpoſe while ſhe covertly ſent Supplys of Men and Money into that Kingdom, ſhe publiſh'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54547:6"/> her ſtricteſt Prohibitions to prevent the <hi>Tranſportation</hi> of <hi>Arms</hi> thither, yet underhand encourag'd her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to carry ſupplys to that <hi>Crown,</hi> as the only means to purchaſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Reputation; yet all this while carry'd fair with the <hi>Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> who made loud complaints of theſe Breaches, eſpecially when he ſaw that the Marquiſs of <hi>Beauveau</hi> had permiſſion to levy a Regiment of <hi>Cavalry</hi> for the Service of that <hi>Crown</hi> in the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> juſt under his Noſe; after he had Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl'd to outward appearance with the <hi>Portugal</hi> Embaſſador, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality with the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> After all which proceedings ſhe would needs have it, that whatever the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſador ſaid, was but the effect of his Fancy and Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54547:7"/> as now at this very time ſhe would make us believe that ſhe has no Deſign to make a War, tho ſhe has eaten up a <hi>Country</hi> within theſe few Months, to which ſhe has no Right at all, and to which ſhe has not the leaſt of Lawful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, if <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> were the Rule of her Actions.</p>
               <p>All this while, though we have obſerv'd all along theſe Practiſes of <hi>France,</hi> without the leaſt oppoſition, yet neither do we make any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of them at this day, that we ſee our ſelves juſt ready to be made the <hi>Unfortunate Victims</hi> of Her <hi>Ambition.</hi> 'Tis true I know there are ſeveral who will reply that <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours</hi> have been ſent to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> which if it were done, we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54547:7"/> having a deeper <hi>Fore-ſight</hi> than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, could not ſuffer us to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd, without doing at leaſt what was his <hi>Duty</hi> to do; which is the reaſon we find him ſo firmly bent againſt the <hi>Perſecutions</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which eſteems not Vertue, but when it agrees with Her Intereſt.</p>
               <p>But to return to the buſineſs, I ſay that <hi>France</hi> endeavour'd to blear the Eyes of the <hi>Spaniſh Embaſſador,</hi> who had in mind however to hunt the wrong Deer, when an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>Accident</hi> made her act with more <hi>boldneſs,</hi> and forbear any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to diſguiſe her Thoughts. She had treated with <hi>Montgeorges,</hi> who was ſlain in the late Wars, and who was then a Captain in <hi>Candale,</hi> a ſtout Soldier, and one who lov'd War a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54547:8"/> all things, to carry a Supply of Officers and Soldiers into <hi>Portugal:</hi> Now <hi>Montgeorges,</hi> being embark'd with his <hi>Company,</hi> and upon his Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age into <hi>Portugal,</hi> happen'd to be taken by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> which were advertis'd of his <hi>Departure;</hi> upon which there was a neceſſity for <hi>France</hi> to take off her Mask; for that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> began already to talk of cutting off <hi>Montgeorges</hi>'s Head.</p>
               <p>This apparent <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Infidelity</hi> vvas attended by ſeveral others, and yet no <hi>Neighbouring Puiſſance</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpos'd it's <hi>Authority,</hi> to the end theſe things might be regulated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Justice:</hi> Not but that there vvas <hi>Warranty</hi> for the <hi>Pyrenaean Peace;</hi> as vvell as there are novv for the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> but that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54547:8"/> they are ſuch, vvho after the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> of the <hi>Treaty,</hi> never mind aftervvards the <hi>Breaches</hi> vvhich are made of it, ſo that there is not one at this time takes any care to ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuccour to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> vvhoſe <hi>Ruine</hi> is attempted by ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct means. On the other ſide, the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> vvhether they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſenſible, or vvhich is moſt probable, that they underſtand their ovvn <hi>weakneſs,</hi> are contended to ſee themſelves ſo rudely handl'd vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teſtifying the leaſt <hi>Reſentment,</hi> but only by <hi>Complaints,</hi> altogether misbecoming <hi>Soveraign Princes,</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if not proſecuted vvith ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Deeds; ſo that others ſeeing them ſo patiently ſvvallovv all <hi>Affronts,</hi> did not think themſelves oblig'd to take their <hi>Part.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54547:9"/>
               <p>Which <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of theirs vvas certainly moſt apparent upon the Occaſion of an <hi>Accident</hi> that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>London</hi> betvveen Monſieur <hi>d'Estrades</hi> and Monſieur <hi>de Vataville Embaſſadors</hi> of both <hi>Crowns:</hi> For after the Baron of <hi>Vataville</hi> had got the <hi>Precedence</hi> before Monſieur <hi>d'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strades,</hi> upon the Entry of another <hi>Embaſſador; Spain</hi> did not only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim and diſavovv the <hi>Act,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo has for ever ſtain'd her <hi>Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by an <hi>Ignominious Declaration,</hi> vvhich I dare not repeat, and vvhich I cannot remember with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bluſhing out of my <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to the Nation. However if the thing be call'd to mind, we ought to lay the Fault upon thoſe other <hi>Potentates,</hi> that ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo paſſionately earneſt for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54547:9"/> Peace, that they never laid to heart the <hi>Affront</hi> which was offer'd to <hi>Spain,</hi> who ſeeing her ſelf aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd by all the World, was forc'd to abate of her wonted Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs the more notable <hi>Head-pieces,</hi> perceiving how proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>France</hi> behav'd her ſelf upon that occaſion were of opinion, that it was neceſſary to withſtand Her <hi>Ambition</hi> before the further Encreaſe of her Strength and Power: But the Councel of theſe prudent <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians</hi> was liſten'd to by way of <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> only, and the Seizure of <hi>Blindneſs</hi> began to be ſo general, that they look'd upon thoſe who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd at that rate, as Perſons that rather ſought to diſturb than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Peace ſo neceſſary for all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54547:10"/>
               <p>Nor did they begin to unhood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wink their Eyes; till <hi>France,</hi> no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to continue quiet, reſolv'd to carry the War into <hi>Flanders</hi> under <hi>Pretences</hi> altogether as <hi>Chymerical</hi> as thoſe at preſent; But with an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſuch a one as they vvere careful to chuſe out of the ſharpeſt witted of the <hi>Chiurme,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to beautifie with a ſpecious varniſh, an <hi>Undertaking,</hi> which a <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Honesty</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> would have been very much troubl'd to perform; only he who had ſerv'd his <hi>Apprentiſhip</hi> at the <hi>Pettie Bar,</hi> where for <hi>Two Crowns,</hi> they will defend the wickedeſt <hi>Injustice</hi> in the World, was of Opinion, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much better <hi>feed</hi> than ſo, it did not become him to neglect ſo fare an Opportunity for his <hi>Preferment:</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54547:10"/> So that <hi>Intereſt</hi> prevailing above <hi>Truth,</hi> in a ſhort time there came forth a <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> wherein they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to maintain, that though the King by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty had renounc'd all manner of <hi>Pretences</hi> which he might hereafter have to the <hi>Low Countries</hi> or <hi>Netherlands,</hi> in right of his Wife, that <hi>Renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was invalid, becauſe the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> had never confirm'd the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Manifesto</hi> endeavour'd further to prove, that the <hi>Queen</hi> had a <hi>Right</hi> to ſeveral <hi>Provinces;</hi> and therefore to give the <hi>Manifeſto</hi> a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle proper to what they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make out, it was Entitul'd <hi>The Rights of the Queen.</hi> For you muſt underſtand, that it was the King himſelf, who had hindr'd the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54547:11"/> 
                  <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty from being Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to the end that for the future it might ſerve for a <hi>Pretence</hi> againſt what had been <hi>ſign'd</hi> by Himſelf, and the chiefeſt <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which piece of Litigious Craft when it gave occaſion to all the World to reflect upon the <hi>Small Faith</hi> and <hi>Sincerity</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> King, Men vvere ſurpriz'd with wonder, That ſo great a Prince, who affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Title of moſt <hi>Christian King</hi> ſhould commit ſuch Violences as would make <hi>Infidels</hi> to bluſh; and took pleaſure to recount his <hi>Actions,</hi> that by comparing the one with the other, the diſadvantage might the better appear on the Kings ſide. The general queſtion was, whether a man were not oblig'd to keep his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54547:11"/> Word which he had ſo ſolemnly ſworn upon the Goſpels, confirm'd by ſo Great and Near an <hi>Alliance,</hi> and where there was nothing omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to render inviolable by all the moſt conſiderable <hi>Acts</hi> that could be performed? And then the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was whether there were any thing that could diſoblige a Man from an Oath ſo ſolemn? to which the <hi>General</hi> Anſwer was, that it was an <hi>Action</hi> dreaded by Men, and which call'd for the juſt <hi>Vengeance</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>And indeed there needs no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Skill in <hi>Theology</hi> to underſtand, that <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> which is the ſame Thing, ſufficiently tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches us, that we are to keep our Words, not only to a <hi>Father-in-Law,</hi> as this occaſion requir'd, but alſo to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54547:12"/> a <hi>Turk.</hi> There is a notable <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of this in the Perſon of a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman of the Family of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glure,</hi> from whence there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral who derive their Deſcent that live in great ſplendor to this day. The particular Hiſtory of this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily relates, that one of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors being taken in Fight by <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladin, Sultan</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was ſet at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty after a long Impriſonment, upon condition that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn himſelf in Perſon with the <hi>Ranſom</hi> which the <hi>Soladin</hi> had laid upon his Head; the <hi>Gentleman</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home, and having ſold part of his <hi>Eſtate</hi> to make good his <hi>Word,</hi> return'd back to <hi>Soladin,</hi> and told him he had brought his <hi>Ranſom in Perſon</hi> according to his own <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Conditions,</hi> and that if he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54547:12"/> pleas'd to name any <hi>Perſon</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it he vvould preſently tell it out. <hi>Soladin,</hi> vvho never thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of him, but believ'd, that ſince he had let him go, he ſhould never ſee him again, vvas ſo ſurpriz'd at his <hi>Generoſity,</hi> that after he had embrac'd and careſs'd him vvith all imaginable <hi>Endearment,</hi> he told him, that from thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he ſhould have a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for the <hi>Christians</hi> than ever he had; and thereupon he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>releaſe</hi> him of his <hi>Ranſom,</hi> but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his <hi>Treaſurer</hi> to give him <hi>Ten Thouſand Franks,</hi> which vvas a great Sum in thoſe days. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſir'd his <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> and that alvvays the <hi>Eldeſt</hi> of his <hi>Family</hi> might be called <hi>Saladin,</hi> to the end that if Poſterity ſhould be curious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54547:13"/> to know why they bore a <hi>Name</hi> ſo extraordinary among the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> they might be inform'd at the ſame time of the Occaſion: Which <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> of <hi>Soladin</hi> has been obſerv'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince; inſomuch that the Count <hi>Deſtoges,</hi> the Eldeſt of the <hi>Family,</hi> is this day nam'd <hi>Soladin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I might be permitted to make <hi>Reflexions</hi> upon this <hi>Story,</hi> I could without difficulty prove, that the <hi>preſent</hi> is far different from the <hi>Ages past.</hi> Formerly they kept their <hi>word</hi> with <hi>Turks,</hi> now adays, a moſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King</hi> will not keep his <hi>Faith</hi> with his <hi>Father-in-Law.</hi> At this day the <hi>Deſcendants</hi> from a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Race are <hi>Chriſtened Saladine;</hi> becauſe their <hi>Anceſtor</hi> ſo promis'd to the <hi>Turk.</hi> At this preſent a <hi>moſt Chriſtian King</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther minds the word, which his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54547:13"/> have paſt to their <hi>Subjects</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> nor the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> which he has made himſelf: At this day the Family of <hi>Anglure,</hi> which is only a private <hi>Gentleman's,</hi> derives all it's Honour from the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Act</hi> of one of its <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> who made good his profligated <hi>Faith</hi> to the <hi>Turk;</hi> but the Houſe of <hi>France,</hi> the moſt renowned in the World, for the <hi>Breach</hi> of an <hi>Infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the <hi>Edicts,</hi> granted in favour of the <hi>Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to our Subject, the King of <hi>France,</hi> grounding his <hi>Claims</hi> upon <hi>Imaginary Pretences,</hi> and upon a <hi>Nicety,</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> had not ratify'd the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to break the <hi>Peace,</hi> and carry his Arms into <hi>Flanders.</hi> But here before I go any further give me
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54547:14"/> leave to tell the World, what the Authority of this <hi>Parliament</hi> is, to prevent the Miſtake of thoſe, who may think it equal in <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> You are then to underſtand that the ſlighteſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Council</hi> cancels all <hi>Edicts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of which is ſo limited at this day, that though it take <hi>Cognizance</hi> only of private and particular <hi>Intereſts,</hi> the <hi>Council</hi> ſends for the <hi>Cauſe</hi> before themſelves and laughs at all that the <hi>Parliament</hi> has done in the ſame Caſe. Former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nevertheleſs it's Authority was very great, nor was it long ago, that it was grown to that height, that every one admired at it; I mean during the Minority of the King: But there is ſuch an <hi>Alteration</hi> ſince that time, that there is little notice taken of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54547:14"/>
               <p>And indeed at that very time, when the forementioned <hi>Manifeſto</hi> appear'd, the King took away all their Privileges, baniſhed all thoſe that were ſuſpected to have any affection for the <hi>publick Interest,</hi> and in a word, contemned it ſo far that he never went thither, but in his <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Boots</hi> and his <hi>Cane</hi> in his Hand. He alſo deprived it of its very Name, as he ſerv'd the reſt of the <hi>Tribunals:</hi> For to make it appear, that there were no more Maſters but himſelf, he ſet forth an <hi>Edict,</hi> That neither the <hi>Parliament</hi> nor the <hi>Grand Councel,</hi> nor the <hi>Chamber of Accompts,</hi> nor the <hi>Court of Aydes</hi> ſhould be called by any other Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle than that of <hi>Superiour,</hi> whereas before they were call'd <hi>Soveraign Courts.</hi> He alſo put forth another
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54547:15"/> 
                  <hi>Edict,</hi> which ſavoured in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of much more wrong and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice: For whereas, when any new Impoſition was thought upon and laid upon the People, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Innovation was impoſed upon the Government, the King was wont to go in Perſon to ſee thoſe <hi>Edicts</hi> ratifyed; the <hi>Parliament</hi> is now obliged to make the <hi>Ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> upon a bare <hi>Letter</hi> under the Privy Signet, many times carryed by a Footman; So that this great <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> formerly erected to be a <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> between the King and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to preſerve the one from the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of the other, is now it ſelf enforced to bow and crouch to the <hi>Kings Will:</hi> For now they dare not make thoſe Remonſtrances, which formerly they did, nor plead
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54547:15"/> as before in behalf of the <hi>People.</hi> Or if they are permitted to make any <hi>Addreſſes</hi> of that Nature, they muſt be full of <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Disſimulation;</hi> and as ſome Parents humble their Children to kiſs the Rod after Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; ſo it behoves the People, who are the Kings Children, or ſhould be ſo at leaſt, to thank the King by the Mouths of their <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> for all the Taxes and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Impoſitions, which he lays up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ſatisfy his profuſion.</p>
               <p>Upon this <hi>Authority,</hi> which the <hi>Parliament</hi> has in the Kingdom it was, That the King laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of an approaching War. In a Word, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was not ſooner dead, but preſently there appeared a ſmall <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> under the Title of <hi>The Rights of the Queen,</hi> by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54547:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54547:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54547:17"/> which they endeavoured to prove, that the Renunciation of all Claims which the King had made by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty was utterly void, becauſe it was never verifyed by the <hi>Parliament.</hi> And yet if the <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation</hi> had been good, which they did not much matter to diſpute, it could not have been long in force, by reaſon that the <hi>Dauphin</hi> had not ratifyed the Treaty, who might pretend a greater Intereſt as being his <hi>Mothers</hi> Heir. In truth, this <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> was nothing but a Compoſure of Words well put together, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining very little or no reaſon. For to begin with the firſt, true it is, That the <hi>Parliament</hi> were wont to ratify the moſt remarkable Acts of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but that ſuch a <hi>Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> was abſolutely Eſſential is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54547:17"/> that which we deny, and which I ſhall endeavour to prove: For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if the King happens to marry with any <hi>Foreign</hi> Princeſs, the <hi>Parliament</hi> has nothing to do with the <hi>Contract:</hi> Nor do we find, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> had any knowledg of that between <hi>H.</hi> 4. and <hi>Marie Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci;</hi> or which is ſtill freſh in <hi>Memory,</hi> of the <hi>Marriage</hi> between the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> and <hi>Madam</hi> the <hi>Dauphineſs.</hi> And yet the <hi>Affairs</hi> tranſacted were as important, as perhaps the Kings <hi>Renunciation</hi> made by the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty: But ſome perhaps will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, That the Caſe is far different; For in a <hi>Treaty</hi> of Peace is ſtated and handled the Eſtabliſhment of the Peoples Peace; whereas in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Marriage</hi> there is nothing tranſacted, but the Concern of two
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54547:18"/> 
                  <hi>Perſons.</hi> I confeſs the reaſon ſeems plauſible but eaſie to refute: For if it be in reſpect of the Peoples In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt that a Treaty of Peace ought to be ratifyed by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> why are not the <hi>Treaties</hi> of <hi>War</hi> ratifyed in the ſame manner? They will have a Treaty which exterminates War, and reſtores Peace to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, inſtead of Trouble and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion that Reigned there before, to be ſubject to a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but they will not have a Treaty of <hi>War,</hi> that baniſhes Peace, and brings in Diſorder and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be ratifyed by <hi>Parliament,</hi> which nevertheleſs was inſtituted to no other end than the Preſervation of the People. Let us rather ſay, that the Cuſtom of verifying <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of Peace in this manner was not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54547:18"/> introduced, till after it was ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that all the Royal Benevolences ſhould be ratifyed in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that ſuch as were not ſo verifyed, ſhould be of no value, which was done to prevent Princes who are generally prone to profuſe Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, from giving away all their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, and being afterwards ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd, for want of Money to vex the People. Let us grant then ſay I, that the Parliament, ſetting that by ſome Treaties of Peace, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Alienations were made from the Crown, chiefly under <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> to free himſelf out of the hands of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards under <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>First,</hi> to deliver himſelf out of the hands of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> had Authority given them to verify Treaties of Peace,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54547:19"/> to prevent the Diſtipation of the Crown Revenues. But their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is yet greater, when it ſhall be a Law received in <hi>France,</hi> that the Parliament may vacate Treaties which are not verifyed, that is to ſay, if the Treaties were not made in due Form, or were found preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the People.</p>
               <p>But it cannot be ſaid, that <hi>France</hi> receiv'd any prejudice by the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean</hi> Treaty, or that the Treaty was not concluded with all the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Formalities. In reſpect of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities</hi> there were ſo many obſerv'd as took up much more time than was neceſſary for the Repoſe of the People, who after ſo tedious a War, thirſted after nothing ſo much as Peace; nor was it enough that <hi>De Lionne</hi> and <hi>Pimentell</hi> ſet their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54547:19"/> hands to the Treaty, but to render it more ſolemn; Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> and <hi>Lewis de Haro,</hi> the Principal Miniſters of both Crowns, were oblig'd to ſign it alſo, ſo that we may ſay that it was the moſt <hi>Authentick Treaty</hi> that had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in a long time before. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they had obſerv'd all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances imaginable, inſomuch that the place appointed for the Conferences, was neither in <hi>France</hi> nor in <hi>Spain,</hi> which nevertheleſs is very remarkable: For that then they were willing, that <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould go cheek by jowle with <hi>France;</hi> yet afterwards they would not allow that the <hi>Treaty</hi> had been ratify'd: But that which ſeemed to put the Treaty not only out of the King's but out of the reach of all <hi>France</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54547:20"/> to do it Injury was that the chiefeſt of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Nobility</hi> had ſign'd the <hi>Contract</hi> of <hi>Marriage</hi> between the King and the <hi>Infanta,</hi> wherein the aforeſaid <hi>Renunciation</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd. So that it was an idle thing to ſay that the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which at moſt does but repreſent the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or Eſtates of the Kingdom would not approve a Treaty, which was already approv'd by the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> and the <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that this <hi>Treaty</hi> brought no prejudice to <hi>France</hi> is as eaſie to prove: For though <hi>France</hi> at that time had a great advantage over <hi>Spain,</hi> we muſt conſider neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that this advantage might one day turn againſt it ſelf, as being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſhare it's <hi>Conqueſts</hi> with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:54547:20"/> then in <hi>Alliance</hi> with her. Now not to mention in the leaſt what are the dangerous <hi>Conſequences</hi> that I could draw from ſuch a <hi>Partition,</hi> it ſhall ſuffice to ſay, That the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was not to let the <hi>Engliſh</hi> get Footing in <hi>Flanders,</hi> who were an Enemy much more dangerous than the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Beſides, <hi>France</hi> by that Treaty had made ſure of the greateſt part of Her <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> and had changed into a certain <hi>Right</hi> the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> which was a <hi>Right</hi> ſubject to ſeveral <hi>Chances</hi> of <hi>Fortune;</hi> and then to object that the <hi>Dauphin</hi> had not ratify'd the Queens <hi>Renunciation</hi> is an Objection ſo weak that it does not deſerve an <hi>Anſwer:</hi> For I wouln fain know, whether a <hi>Father</hi> and a <hi>Mother</hi> do not bind their <hi>Iſſue</hi> when they ſign a <hi>Contract?</hi> And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54547:21"/> whether the <hi>Dauphin</hi> had more <hi>right</hi> to queſtion that which the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> had ſign'd, than they who live under the ſame Laws and the ſame <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe <hi>Conſiderations</hi> give us plainly to ſee that whatever of <hi>Right</hi> belonging to the Queen was in the <hi>Treaty,</hi> was only to amuſe the <hi>Common People,</hi> and particularly thoſe of <hi>Flanders,</hi> who being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the <hi>Queen</hi> had a <hi>Right</hi> to the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> were in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to foment a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to which they might be provok'd by the ill <hi>Uſage</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh Soldiery,</hi> who for want of <hi>Pay,</hi> commit many <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences</hi> and <hi>Diſorders.</hi> It being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great piece of <hi>Prudence</hi> to prevent all Trouble that might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from thence, the Baron of <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54547:21"/> one of the Miniſters of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> put Pen to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to ſhew the Vanity of the Conſequences, which the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Author of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> drew from the <hi>Right</hi> of the <hi>Queen.</hi> Of which a great number of <hi>Copies</hi> were ſent into <hi>Flanders, Germany</hi> and the <hi>Neighbouring Parts;</hi> ſome were alſo conveyed into <hi>France;</hi> but the Court reſolving that the People ſhould make it's <hi>Ambition</hi> an <hi>Article</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> made ſuch an exact <hi>Enquiry</hi> after the <hi>Publiſhers</hi> that two or three were committed to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> and were in great danger of their Lives. For as it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in that Kingdom to write <hi>Truth,</hi> either in <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Politicks,</hi> neither was it permitted to be ſpoken or taught to any one whatſoever. And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54547:22"/> therefore as well they who bought the <hi>Book,</hi> as they who publiſhed theſe <hi>Books</hi> were oblig'd to keep out of the way, as if they had been <hi>Malefactors.</hi> But the more they thought to reſtrain the Peoples Wills, the more the People endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to ſet their minds at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that many honeſt Folks made it their buſineſs to content their <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,</hi> in ſpight of all the <hi>publick Prohibitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By vertue of theſe <hi>Imaginary Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions</hi> the King fail'd not to ſend to the <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> to ſurrender into his hands thoſe <hi>places,</hi> which, as he pretended, belong'd to the <hi>Queen.</hi> And becauſe he could not chooſe but know, that the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> would no way anſwer his <hi>Expectations,</hi> he follow'd the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54547:22"/> with a puiſſant <hi>Army,</hi> to make himſelf the Maſter of them by force; thereupon, having received the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors</hi> Anſwer, that the <hi>King</hi> his Maſter would fairly part with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he enter'd <hi>Flanders,</hi> took <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy, Aeth, Courtray, Audenard</hi> and <hi>Liſle,</hi> while the Marſhal <hi>D'Aumont</hi> with another Army attack'd the <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Towns</hi> that lay nearer the Sea.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Conqueſts</hi> carried on with ſuch a <hi>rapid Succeſs,</hi> aſtoniſh'd the <hi>Neighbouring States,</hi> who thought it their <hi>Interest</hi> to ſtop theſe <hi>violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings;</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> who by no means liked the near <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach</hi> of ſo formidable and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious a <hi>Neighbour:</hi> Therefore they engaged the King of <hi>England</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a League, wherein the King
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54547:23"/> of <hi>Swedeland</hi> alſo joyn'd, by which they obliged themſelves all three, to make the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> lay down their Arms, with a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to declare a War againſt the obſtinate Refuſer.</p>
               <p>This <hi>League</hi> was call'd the <hi>Triple Alliance,</hi> afterwards ſo fatal to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as I ſhall relate in due Place, that it may be thought they had reaſon enough to repent their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation. They ſay it was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Rochel,</hi> who laid the firſt Foundations of it, after he had made thoſe <hi>Powerful Princes</hi> deeply ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how little the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was to be truſted; however it were, <hi>France,</hi> who ſeldom eaſily pardons thoſe that have once offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her, well knowing that the ſame Perſon was in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54547:23"/> to inſinuate the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion among the <hi>Cantons,</hi> ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the two <hi>Platells,</hi> of which the Eldeſt was a Captain of Horſe, the other Eſquire to <hi>Monſieur Turenne,</hi> to apprehend him. It had been a knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Enterprize</hi> and of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence for the <hi>Platells,</hi> had their <hi>Errand</hi> been diſcovered in <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But being ſo cunning as to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their buſineſs private, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Perſon, as he paſſed from one City to another, they carry'd him into <hi>France,</hi> where he was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken alive upon the Wheel, after he had endeavour'd to eſcape the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Execution, by an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more reſolute than <hi>Christian-like:</hi> For having found in the hole of the <hi>Priſon,</hi> where he lay a piece of <hi>Glaſs,</hi> he cut off his <hi>Privy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:54547:24"/> and hid them under the Bed, that the <hi>Jaylor</hi> might not know what he had done: but in regard he could not ſtanch the blood ſo well but that ſome drops would fall from the wound, beſides that his Colour plainly ſhewed that ſomething more than ordinary ailed him, the Jaylor would ſee whence the Blood came: So that after a ſhort ſearch having found, what was hidden under the Bed, all in a puddle of Blood; he went and gave the <hi>Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> notice of it, who being reſolv'd to make him a publick <hi>Example</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd to give Sentence. Thereupon they condemn'd him to be broken upon the Wheel, and fearing he might not have ſtrength enough to be carry'd to the common place of Execution, or that he might dye,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54547:24"/> if they delay'd till the Afternoon, Order was given for the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Erecting of a Scaffold before the <hi>Priſon-door,</hi> and for his ſpeedy <hi>Execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Triple Alliance,</hi> which <hi>France</hi> did not foreſee, aſtoniſh'd her ſo, that altho ſhe had promis'd her ſelf the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of the greateſt Part of all <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſhe was oblig'd never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs to lay down her <hi>Arms;</hi> not but then ſhe had an <hi>Army</hi> on foot of above a <hi>Hundred Thouſand Men,</hi> but in regard that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> made great <hi>Preparations</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> and that ſhe had no <hi>Fleet</hi> was able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt two ſuch <hi>potent Enemies,</hi> ſhe was afraid, leaſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> while her <hi>Forces</hi> were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in <hi>Flanders,</hi> might land either in <hi>Normandy</hi> or <hi>Britainy,</hi> and ſtrike
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54547:25"/> a panick Terror into the heart of his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> having thus made a <hi>Peace,</hi> as it were by <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> ſhe plotted nothing more, than to revenge her ſelf upon thoſe, who had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted moſt effectually toward it. Now it being apparent that the <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces</hi> had been moſt active upon that occaſion, and that all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> owed the <hi>Peace</hi> which it enjoy'd to <hi>Them,</hi> it was their <hi>Lot</hi> to feel the weight of his <hi>Fury;</hi> yet was ſhe careful to watch her <hi>Opportunity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe brake forth into an open <hi>Blaze</hi> of <hi>Revenge:</hi> For <hi>Holland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet in League with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Swedland,</hi> therefore there muſt be a way found out to divide her from two ſuch <hi>Potent Friends,</hi> who being <hi>United</hi> were ſtill ſufficiently
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54547:25"/> powerful to diſappoint all the <hi>French</hi> Deſigns: Which as <hi>France</hi> had ſtill watch'd to bring to paſs, it was not long before an Opportunity offer'd it ſelf, by reaſon of an unhappy <hi>difference</hi> between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> about <hi>Trade.</hi> Nor did <hi>France</hi> then take any care as ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done, to offer her Mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to cloſe up the breach between the <hi>Two Nations,</hi> but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſed all means to incenſe the King of <hi>England,</hi> yet underhand ſet on foot a <hi>Treaty</hi> with the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> leaſt they ſhould have any thoughts of making <hi>Peace</hi> with <hi>Great Britain.</hi> The <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who had often prov'd the good Effects of the <hi>French</hi> Succours, when they had any quarrel with <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd they would be ſtill as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54547:26"/> depending upon the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who ceaſed not to amuſe 'em with daily hopes: But while they were thus as they thought, upon a concluſion with Him, to oppoſe the King of <hi>England,</hi> who was making powerful <hi>Preparations</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 'em by <hi>Sea,</hi> they were not a little ſurpriz'd to find that the two <hi>Princes</hi> were joyn'd both together, and that while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> attack'd 'em by <hi>Sea,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> were to fall upon them by Land, and that with a Force ſo numerous and dreadful, that the Memory of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> had not Parallel'd the like out of <hi>France</hi> in a long time: And then it was that the <hi>United Provinces</hi> found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſtrange <hi>Diſorder;</hi> for tho they wanted neither <hi>Ships,</hi> nor <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> yet had they not an <hi>Army</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54547:26"/> to oppoſe the King of <hi>France</hi> who had brought his Forces alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into the <hi>Country</hi> about <hi>Cologne,</hi> from whence he intended to make the Attack.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of theſe <hi>Troubles</hi> to levy Men in <hi>Holland,</hi> was look'd upon as a Remedy that would but little avail; when Peace enjoy'd for ſo many years had render'd the <hi>People</hi> more fit for <hi>Trade</hi> than <hi>War;</hi> raw <hi>Souldiers</hi> not being proper to make reſiſtance againſt inur'd and hardy <hi>veterans:</hi> Therefore the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> ſent into <hi>Germany</hi> to raiſe <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and to treat with thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> from whom they expected aid; but all <hi>Europe</hi> was ſo aſtoniſh'd at the prodigious <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Preparations</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> that every one kept his own Force at home, out of a Jealouſie,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54547:27"/> leaſt <hi>France,</hi> under a pretence of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailing the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> ſhould break into <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> at that time had no more than <hi>Five and Twenty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men;</hi> for tho they had given out <hi>Commisſions</hi> to all that proffered their Service, yet they could rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon upon none but thoſe that were drawn down to the general <hi>Rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouze.</hi> But that which yet enfeebl'd their <hi>Condition</hi> the more was, that <hi>De Wit,</hi> the <hi>Penſionary</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> had always kept the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at a diſtance from the Management of <hi>Affairs;</hi> and therefore being a better <hi>Politician</hi> than <hi>Souldier,</hi> yet one who would have a hand in every thing, the main buſineſs was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with much <hi>Diſorder</hi> and <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> There was alſo one thing more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54547:27"/> which very much contributed to the <hi>Ruin</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> tho at that time not diſcovered, which was that the King of <hi>France</hi> had Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of every thing that was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Country by means of <hi>Mombas,</hi> then in the Service of the <hi>Republic,</hi> which had given him a conſiderable <hi>Command</hi> in the <hi>Army:</hi> He was a <hi>Frenchman</hi> born, ſo that he was eaſily gain'd to the King, by the <hi>Induſtry</hi> of <hi>Des Roches</hi> Captain of the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s Guards, and his near <hi>Relation,</hi> and who had prevail'd with him to take a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into <hi>France</hi> the Winter before, where he had been diſcourſed with by <hi>Monſieur</hi> the <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Conjuncture of <hi>Accidents</hi> had been ſufficient to have utterly ruined the <hi>State,</hi> according to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54547:28"/> probability, had not God determin'd the contrary. At what time, the King of <hi>France</hi> being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to enter the Country, the <hi>States</hi> aſſembled together to conſider of the beſt way for the <hi>Defence</hi> of their <hi>Dominions:</hi> Monſieur the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> who maugre all the ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and juggling of <hi>De Wit,</hi> was choſen <hi>Captain General</hi> for the <hi>States,</hi> advis'd the quitting of all the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces above the <hi>Rhine,</hi> to put in <hi>Ten Thouſand</hi> Souldiers into <hi>Maestrick,</hi> and to encamp with the reſt at <hi>Bode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave,</hi> as being a moſt advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Poſt to ſecure <hi>Holland.</hi> Monſieur <hi>D' Opdam</hi> and <hi>Celidrek,</hi> who ſpake in the behalf of the Nobility, were of the ſame Opinion; but the reſt being of a contrary <hi>Judgmeni,</hi> it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that they ſhould hold all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54547:28"/> Places beyond the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which nevertheleſs they very much weaken'd by draining thoſe Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſupply <hi>Maeſtrick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean while, the King ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lain for ſome time before <hi>Charleroy,</hi> march'd in view of <hi>Maeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> and ſtay'd ſome <hi>Twelve</hi> or <hi>Fifteen</hi> Days before <hi>Wiſe,</hi> a ſmall Town in the Territory of <hi>Liege,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he clapt a <hi>Garriſon;</hi> there having received <hi>Intelligence</hi> from <hi>Mombas,</hi> that all the Towns above the <hi>Rhine</hi> were ſlenderly mann'd, and almoſt naked of Defence, he paſs'd the <hi>Meuſe</hi> at <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and after he had beaten off certain Troops that were advantageouſly poſted, he ſate down before <hi>Orſoy</hi> with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal <hi>Siege.</hi> The <hi>Governor</hi> wanted no Courage, but in regard the <hi>Town</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54547:29"/> was neither ſtrong of it ſelf, nor ſufficiently <hi>Garriſoned,</hi> he ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his <hi>Charge</hi> the day following. The <hi>French</hi> plunder'd the <hi>Town,</hi> and hang'd up all thoſe of their own Nation that they found in Arms, and among the reſt one Man that was <hi>Threeſcore</hi> and <hi>ſix</hi> years of <hi>Age,</hi> who was the chief Canonier in <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoy.</hi> From thence the Army mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Rhineberg,</hi> which <hi>Doſſery</hi> ſurrendr'd without ſtriking a ſtroak. For which not long after the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> caus'd his Head to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from his Shoulders. Nor did the Governor of <hi>Weſel</hi> make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance much more to his Honour; though the Place was able to have ſuſtained a long <hi>Siege,</hi> who ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it to the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> after and Entrenchment of two or three
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54547:29"/> days. Whoſe <hi>Puniſhment</hi> therefore though not ſo ſevere as <hi>Doſsory</hi>'s, was ſomething like it: For the Hangman skimm'd his Sword o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Head, but ſpar'd him his Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious Life. <hi>Buric</hi> was at the ſame time taken by Marſhel <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne.</hi> After which the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> advanc'd into the Country, and took in <hi>Deudetrom, Rees</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meric</hi> with the ſame <hi>Eaſe</hi> that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd other Places.</p>
               <p>Theſe Victories though they coſt but little Blood, gave the King of <hi>France</hi> the Reputation of a <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Army. For they ſaw that he might ſay like Him, <hi>I came, I viewed and vanquiſhed,</hi> Therefore to uphold the Glory he had won, he reſolved to paſs the <hi>Rhine,</hi> as formerly that <hi>Emperor</hi> had done; but he would
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54547:30"/> paſs it after a more Noble and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Manner: For <hi>Caeſar</hi> had paſs'd it by the means of a <hi>Bridge,</hi> but he was reſolv'd to ſwim it over.</p>
               <p>Two Gentlemen of the <hi>Country,</hi> Neighbors to <hi>Tholus,</hi> whoſe Names I cannot well remember, came to the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> at <hi>Emeric,</hi> and offer'd to ſhew him a <hi>Place,</hi> where he had but an hundred <hi>Paces</hi> to ſwim. He gladly accepted their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, which made the <hi>French</hi> now look upon themſelves at the End of their <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> in regard the <hi>Iſſel</hi> ſtopped their Entrance into the <hi>Country,</hi> not only becauſe of its depth, but alſo by reaſon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lay ſtrongly entrench'd on the other ſide of the <hi>River.</hi> Thereupon the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> having high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly careſſes'd the two <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54547:30"/> promiſing them large <hi>Reward's</hi> commanded the Count <hi>de Guiche</hi> to go along with them, to try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he might confide in what they had ſaid; immediately they carried the Count right againſt <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and throwing themſelves firſt into the Water, the Count follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Squire, while his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſtayed behind by the <hi>River</hi> ſide: Upon this <hi>Tryal</hi> finding that the Gentlemen had ſpoken nothing but what was <hi>Truth,</hi> the Count return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made his <hi>Report</hi> to the <hi>Prince,</hi> who ſent the <hi>King</hi> an Account of what had happened, adding withal, if he pleaſed to take the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Enterprize</hi> upon himſelf, how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie it would be for him to ſurprize the <hi>Enemy,</hi> who little miſtruſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> and minded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54547:31"/> but to guard the <hi>Iſſel.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> eager in the <hi>Chaſe</hi> of ſo much <hi>Honour,</hi> flew to the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Conde</hi>'s Camp, and after he had ſupped with him, marched all night along the <hi>Bank</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and arrived at the Place about half an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> who found more fidelity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Meaner</hi> Sort than among the <hi>Nobility,</hi> being advertized by the <hi>Boors,</hi> who ſaw the <hi>French,</hi> when they ſounded the <hi>Depth</hi> of the <hi>River,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> had ſome <hi>Deſign</hi> on the other ſide, ſent thither <hi>Mombas</hi> with the <hi>Cavalry</hi> and <hi>Infantry. Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> had already forfeited his <hi>Honour</hi> by keeping Correſpondence with the Enemy, but tho this Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was no leſs favourable for him
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54547:31"/> to continue his <hi>Treacherous</hi> Deſigns, was afraid, that for want of being known, he might run ſome hazard in the <hi>Conflict,</hi> bethought himſelf of writing to the <hi>Deputies</hi> of the <hi>States,</hi> who attended the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> and thereupon ſent them a fair Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that there was no Likelyhood, that the <hi>French</hi> had any Deſign to paſs the River, and that therefore, if they thought good, he would put himſelf into <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> whither it was moſt probable that the <hi>French</hi> intended to march: He took his Time to ſend this Letter when the Prince was abſent from the Camp with a <hi>Detachment;</hi> ſo that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties</hi> not having the leaſt <hi>Miſtruſt</hi> of his <hi>Fidelity,</hi> and believing the Care of <hi>Nimeghen</hi> to be of greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, ſent him Orders to march
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54547:32"/> thither. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the Camp, was ſtrangly ſurprized, to hear what <hi>Mombas</hi> had done, and being now confirmed by this laſt <hi>Action</hi> of his, in ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Suſpitions</hi> he had of his being a <hi>Traitor,</hi> cauſed him to be <hi>Arreſted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which done, he commanded <hi>Wortz</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> whom the <hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick</hi> had taken into their <hi>Services</hi> to march with all ſpeed to <hi>Tholus,</hi> with ſome Companies that were drawn out of the <hi>Army. Wortz</hi> did all he could to haſten his <hi>Entrenchments,</hi> and order'd the <hi>Cavalry</hi> to advance to the ſide of the <hi>River.</hi> Whither the <hi>King</hi> being alſo arriv'd, cauſed ſeveral Pieces of Canon to be brought and levell'd againſt <hi>Wortz</hi>'s Cavalry, who thereupon retired among the <hi>Trees</hi> that grew by the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54547:32"/> banks ſide. In the mean time the <hi>French</hi> threw themſelves into the <hi>River,</hi> where they loſt abundance of Men, who were ſwallowed up in a Gulf, which others obſerving took the advantage of the left hand and forded over like <hi>Cowes,</hi> one at the <hi>Tayl</hi> of the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wortz</hi> his <hi>Cavalry</hi> beheld the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy paſſing the <hi>River,</hi> without ſo much as giving the leaſt Ground, till they ſaw ſome of the <hi>French</hi> Horſe that were paſſed the River, begin to Form themſelves into a Body. And then indeed they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently drew out from among the Trees, but they were ſo far from endeavouring to repel the Enemy, who were retired back into the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that they ſtopped at the River ſide, from whence they diſcharged
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54547:33"/> a Volley of Shot, but at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as did little or no Execution. Which <hi>Cowardiſe</hi> of theirs put Life into the <hi>French,</hi> who had they been vigorouſly purſued into the Water, would never have adventured to make head again, or to have made a ſtand till more aſſiſtance came to their Relief. So that as ſoon as they found themſelves ſtrong enough to march againſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> Horſe, who ſtill kept their Station without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, they marched out of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with their Swords in their hands and put the <hi>Dutch</hi> to flight. Thus <hi>Wortz</hi>'s Cavalry having fordidly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ground, the <hi>French</hi> rallyed and grew ſtronger and ſtronger by the <hi>Addition</hi> of more Force; the <hi>French</hi> continually paſſing the River, ſome wading, others in <hi>Boats.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54547:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> alſo having put himſelf into a Boat with the Duke D' <hi>Angion,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Perſonages of the Court, was got near the oppoſite Shore, when he perceived that <hi>Monſieur de Longueville,</hi> having thrown him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the River, was very near drowning, ſo that he was forc'd to return back, to take him into the Boat; but then ſpeedily recovering the other ſide, he was no ſooner landed but he drew up his Forces into <hi>Battalia,</hi> to attack the Enemies Entrenchments. The <hi>Dutch Infantry</hi> ſeeing but little ſecurity in their ſlender Works, and on the other ſide having put all their confidence in their <hi>Cavalry,</hi> by which they ſaw themſelves now totally abandoned, took more care to crave quarter,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54547:34"/> than to make any reſiſtance, which Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, crying out aloud to them to lay down their <hi>Arms:</hi> All this while the <hi>French</hi> advanced forward without ſo much as diſcharging a Gun on either ſide, ſo that the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who ſaw all that paſſed, thought himſelf ſure of a <hi>Victory</hi> that would coſt no <hi>Blood:</hi> But Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Longueville,</hi> who had been drinking hard at <hi>Emeric,</hi> advancing up to the <hi>Trenches,</hi> let fly a <hi>Pistol,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> not a little aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that they had forborn ſo long, and believing now there was no <hi>Quarter</hi> to be expected, returned in anſwer to the Dukes <hi>Piſtol</hi> ſuch a ſmart Volley, that many of the moſt conſiderable of the Enemy were fetched off their <hi>Horſes.</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54547:34"/> 
                  <hi>Longueville</hi> who began the skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh was killed outright, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> wounded, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers too long to <hi>Catalogue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> at firſt aſtoniſhed at this unexpected <hi>Accident,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered themſelves from their <hi>Fears</hi> rallyed again and fell upon the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments,</hi> where they found ſome <hi>Reſistance;</hi> eſpecially at a <hi>Barricado,</hi> where ſtood a grey haired Officer, but one who notwithſtanding his Years, ſhewed a Courage becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Prime</hi> of vigorous <hi>Youth;</hi> but at length being overlaid with num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the reſt betook themſelves to flight, without demanding <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which they thought would but be in vain.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> having now no Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to fight, pillaged the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54547:35"/> 
                  <hi>Tholus,</hi> and put the Iſland of <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taw</hi> under <hi>Contribution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was this the only advantage which they gained by their Paſſage over the <hi>Rhine;</hi> for the <hi>Hollanders</hi> fearing leaſt the Enemy ſhould come upon their backs, forſoke the <hi>Iſſel,</hi> and retreated to <hi>Utrech,</hi> where the People would have <hi>Sacrificed Mombas</hi> to their Fury, upon whom they laid all the blame of what had happened: But Monſieur the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> though he knew he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Death, but was willing to have him firſt examined, if not put to the Rack, to the end he might underſtand the depth of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, gave Order that he ſhould be conveyed through a <hi>Poſtern,</hi> and hid in a <hi>Hay-loft,</hi> to preſerve him from the Rage of the People. In the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54547:35"/> mean while the King in Perſon took the City of <hi>DOESBERGH,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Turenne</hi> took in <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen, Zuoll, Deventer, Graves, Arn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Skink, Creveceur</hi> and ſeveral other Places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Utrech</hi> alſo fell into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> without the <hi>Conſtraint</hi> of a Siege: For while the King lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Doeſbergh,</hi> the <hi>Burgher-Maſters</hi> of the Town carryed him the Keys, as if they had been afraid they ſhould not have a new Maſter ſoon enough. Thereupon the <hi>Marquiſs</hi> of <hi>Rochford,</hi> in good reputation at <hi>Court</hi> was ſent thither to command in chief: But not having as yet much Experience in War, he omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> which the <hi>Dutch</hi> had quitted; by the poſſeſſion of which they had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54547:36"/> aſſured themſelves of <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> For had they been <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> it had been an eaſie thing to hinder any Veſſels from going in or out from <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> for that they were to paſs by <hi>Maidam,</hi> which they durſt not have attempted, if the <hi>French</hi> had been Maſters of it; which had been the way to have compell'd <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd of it ſelf, as <hi>Utrech</hi> had done: Not but that if the King himſelf had appear'd before the Walls, they had certainly carryed him the <hi>Keys;</hi> in regard that ſuch was the general Deſpair, that every one thought of nothing elſe but to ſave his own Family, not minding the publick Intereſt of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: So that without expecting a Summons from the King, they held
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54547:36"/> a <hi>Councel</hi> in the City, and debated whether they ſhould not go to meet the King, and beſeech him to take as well the City as the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants into his Protection, and it was an <hi>even Lay,</hi> but that they had taken that <hi>Reſolution,</hi> had not two <hi>Burghermaſters,</hi> whoſe Memories ought to be Sacred to Poſterity, and whoſe Names were <hi>Offte</hi> and <hi>Haſſenar,</hi> encouraged the reſt to pluck up good hearts, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to call the Sea to their <hi>Aſſistance</hi> which was a more certain remedy, when they ſhould be reduced to the laſt <hi>Neceſſity</hi> than to receive the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the King had taken the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Doeſbregh,</hi> he encamped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Zeist,</hi> two Leagues from <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trech,</hi> where he was attended by the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54547:37"/> 
                  <hi>States</hi> Embaſſadors with <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> but he being ſwell'd with the <hi>Sueceſs</hi> of his <hi>Arms,</hi> propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſuch rigorous <hi>Conditions,</hi> that the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> were forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn without being able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their <hi>Deſires.</hi> Nevertheleſs, when they arriv'd at the <hi>Hague,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> reſolved to ſend them back again, for that their <hi>Affairs</hi> were then in ſuch a deſperate <hi>Condition,</hi> that they thought themſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, that they could be thought to accept of any manner of <hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was yet another <hi>Difficulty</hi> in the <hi>Treaty;</hi> for that the King would conclude nothing without the King of <hi>England,</hi> who finding the <hi>Conjuncture</hi> favourable, was no leſs ſevere in his <hi>Demands.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54547:37"/>
               <p>The <hi>States</hi> Embaſſadors being returned to <hi>Zeist,</hi> and finding there the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Embaſſadors likewiſe, propoſed a <hi>New Treaty,</hi> but very difficult to conclude: For beſides that the <hi>French</hi> would not remit any thing of their <hi>former Pretenſions,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Propoſals</hi> ran ſo high, that it had been the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> to have agreed them. <hi>France</hi> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a <hi>Medal</hi> every year, by way of <hi>Tribute,</hi> with all the <hi>Expences</hi> of the <hi>War,</hi> which amounted, according to their <hi>Accompts,</hi> to a prodigious <hi>Sum. England</hi> demanded <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Indits,</hi> and ſo many other things which appertained to the <hi>Republick,</hi> ſo that the <hi>States</hi> had as good have abandoned all, as to conclude a Treaty ſo diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous. The <hi>States</hi> being advized of theſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54547:38"/> things by their Embaſſadors, who were returned from <hi>Zeiſt,</hi> reſolv'd to break down their <hi>Dams,</hi> which was their laſt <hi>Remedy</hi> upon the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt pinch of <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> But that which made them take this <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſo much the ſooner, was this, that the People, laying all the blame of their Misfortunes upon thoſe who managed the publick <hi>Affairs,</hi> had maſſacred the <hi>Penſionary</hi> of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> together with his Brother, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that the Face of <hi>Affairs</hi> would change upon the <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>New Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Extremities cauſing the <hi>States</hi> to break up their Dams, gave them leiſure to think and conſider of their <hi>Affairs:</hi> Whereupon they ſent to the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> which both
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54547:38"/> Kings had made them, thereby to prepoſſeſs their minds, with what they began already to harbour, as touching the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> They laid before them the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to which they were reduced, and that if they delayed their <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour</hi> any longer, it would be too late, when they had a deſire to do it. That their preſent <hi>Safety</hi> was in the Water, which could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſecure them. That when the Winter came the <hi>French</hi> would march over the <hi>Ice</hi> to ſtorm their Walls: So that if they could not reſiſt when the <hi>Provinces</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and flouriſhing, there was lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle likelyhood they ſhould now withſtand ſo potent an <hi>Enemy,</hi> when they were fallen from their <hi>ancient</hi> Reputation.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:54547:39"/>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi> of which they could not doubt the <hi>Truth,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the lamentable <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Republick,</hi> mov'd the <hi>Emperor</hi> to pity, as alſo the Marquiſs of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> and ſeveral other Princes of the <hi>Empire:</hi> The Marquiſs of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> as being the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, was the firſt that took the field for their <hi>Relief:</hi> So that the King knowing that he had now to deal with a Prince ſtout, reſolute and a try'd Souldier, rais'd his Camp from before <hi>Zeiſt,</hi> and returned toward <hi>France.</hi> But before his departure he reſolved to try to make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Boyſleduc,</hi> which was block'd up upon one ſide by the Garriſon of <hi>Creveceur</hi> on the other by that of <hi>Endoue Bois le duc,</hi> is a <hi>Town</hi> ſeated in the midſt of a Marſh, but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54547:39"/> notwithſtanding the ſtrength of its Scituation, the Fortifications are but weak. Nevertheleſs there is a Cittadel on that ſide next to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with two Forts on the other ſide next <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> which however would ſignifie little, did not the Situation render it almoſt inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The King took up his Head Quarters at <hi>Boustel,</hi> but while he was preparing all things for a ſeige, God who had began to take <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into His <hi>Protection,</hi> ſent ſuch continual <hi>Rains</hi> for four or five days together, ſo that the Country being Level was immediately all under Water, as if the Sluces had been opened. The King however ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for hard <hi>Weather,</hi> ſtop't at <hi>Bockſtel</hi> for eight or ten days, but finding the <hi>Weather</hi> continue bad,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54547:40"/> he Diſcamped and returned Home.</p>
               <p>And now the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who after the Death of the Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, had the ſole Authority of command conferred upon Him, ſeeing the People in ſome ſort of Repoſe upon the Retreat of the King of <hi>France,</hi> bethought himſelf of giving them yet further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent by the Puniſhment of <hi>Mombas;</hi> whoſe Head they eagerly demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He had been conveyed from <hi>Utrick</hi> to <hi>Wordes,</hi> and from <hi>Wordes</hi> to <hi>Nieurburk,</hi> whether the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was retired. Thereupon the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> call'd a <hi>Counſel of War,</hi> and began to examin the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, which appear'd every day more foul than other; at length his <hi>Conſcience</hi> not permitting him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſt, and giving himſelf for loſt,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54547:40"/> he began to think of making his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, which nevertheleſs was a difficult thing to do, by reaſon he was very ſtrictly guarded, having <hi>Sentinels</hi> at his <hi>Chamber Door,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Windows of his <hi>Lodging:</hi> While he was muſing what courſe to take, one of his <hi>Friends</hi> brought him a <hi>Letter,</hi> which gave him to underſtand that he had but three Days to live, if he did not find ſome way to eſcape: For that the <hi>Council of War</hi> was reſolv'd to make him an <hi>Example</hi> to others, and therefore advis'd him to look to himſelf. <hi>Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> finding himſelf ſo ſeverely threatned, diſcours'd the ſame day with one of his <hi>Guards,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd him for a certain Sum of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> to let him eſcape out at the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, when he ſhould be put to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54547:41"/> ſtand <hi>Sentinel</hi> at that Poſt, which would fall out the next day. Having gone thus far, he alſo ſounded a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Officer, who was to be upon the <hi>Guard</hi> the ſame day, at a deep Water, to know if he would let him paſs that way, and get him a <hi>Guide</hi> ready: The Officer no leſs covetous of Money than the <hi>Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> agreed for an hundred <hi>Piſtols</hi> to all that <hi>Mombas</hi> deſired, The Bargain being thus driven, gave the <hi>Hundred Piſtols</hi> to one <hi>Villare,</hi> who ſerved him in the <hi>Nature</hi> of his <hi>Squire,</hi> and had been an Agent in the buſineſs, to carry them to the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> but <hi>Villare,</hi> inſtead of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to the <hi>Officer,</hi> ran quite away with them; whether it were that he were naturally enclin'd to ſuch kind of <hi>Varlet</hi>'s Tricks, or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54547:41"/> whether his Maſter were in his <hi>Debt,</hi> and ſo he thought to pay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf while he had an opportunity; however it were <hi>Mombas</hi> reckning upon his <hi>Payment,</hi> made it his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs now to deceive the Watch that guarded him in ſight; to which purpoſe,</p>
               <p>He firſt complained of a great <hi>Pain</hi> in his <hi>Leg,</hi> upon which he ſent for a <hi>Chyrurgeon,</hi> and ſhewing him his <hi>Leg,</hi> which by reaſon of a wound he had received was grown bigger than the other: He alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the <hi>Prince</hi> to ſend him one of his <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> who concluded, that his <hi>Grief</hi> required a large Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which they ſent him to apply to the place affected; upon this pretence, he kept his Bed without any Suſpition, and upon the day
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54547:42"/> appointed he ſent for ſome <hi>Tobacco,</hi> telling the <hi>Guards</hi> he would ſmoak a <hi>Pipe</hi> with them after <hi>Supper;</hi> but pretending of a ſuddain to be very ſick, he went to Bed in the <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> preſence, deſiring them withal to ſmoak their <hi>Tobacco</hi> in the next Chamber, becauſe it offended him. The <hi>Souldiers</hi> ſeeing him in Bed, and not dreaming that he had a Deſign to eſcape, preſently withdrew; who were no ſooner out of the Chamber but <hi>Mombas</hi> ſlipt out of his Bed, took the <hi>Plaiſter</hi> from his Leg and clapt it upon his <hi>Eye,</hi> and leapt out at the Window where the <hi>Sentinel</hi> ſtood that had been brib'd, as alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy has been ſaid.</p>
               <p>In this <hi>Diſguiſe</hi> he got through the Camp without being diſcover'd; but when he came to the <hi>Spaniard</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:54547:42"/> he was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd to find, that he would not let him paſs any farther, unleſs he gave him the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pistols</hi> before-hand, which he had promiſed him. By this diſpute <hi>Mombas</hi> preſently diſcovered the Roguery and Treachery of his Man <hi>Villaire;</hi> but there was no retreiving that which was gone; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt now ſatisfie the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> as well as he could; for the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was reſolved he would have his Bargain, and <hi>Mombas</hi> had it not to pay over again. In the end being forced to make a Vertue of Neceſſity, he turned his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets the inſide outermoſt, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him all he had about Him: But ſeeing that nothing but the <hi>Hundred</hi> Piſtols would content him, <hi>Mombas</hi> told the <hi>Officer</hi> that he might
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54547:43"/> do with him as he pleaſed, but if he were the occaſion of his being retaken, he vowed to diſcover him in the firſt place, and therefore bid him quickly conſider, for he had nothing farther to ſay. The Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer terrifyed with theſe <hi>Threats,</hi> took what <hi>Mombas</hi> was able to give him and let him paſs with his <hi>Guides.</hi> After this <hi>Mombas</hi> waded up to the Waſt in Water for three Leagues together, very often in danger of being drown'd. But it was but juſt that a Traitor who had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the Ruin of a Nation, ſhould have his turn of Miſery; who tho he endured a large Portion of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune and Hardſhip, yet ſuffered not the <hi>half</hi> of what he deſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mombas</hi> being thus arrived at <hi>Wordes,</hi> after he had endured an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54547:43"/> of Diſaſters more eaſie to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine than to deſcribe, took a Room in the Boat that goes from <hi>Wordes</hi> to <hi>Uytrecht,</hi> but he was no ſooner ſat down, but he perceived that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who ſat next him, knew him and had told his Name to another Woman that ſat next to her. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in a Peck of Troubles he quitted the Boat, being reſolved to take ſome other way. But not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to adventure the High road for fear of being known, he threw himſelf into any other guide then his own deſpair, having neither <hi>Sous</hi> nor <hi>Doit</hi> to help himſelf.</p>
               <p>When he came within a quarter of a League of <hi>Utrecht</hi> he forſook the Water, but ſo bedaub'd with Mud and Dirt, that there was no poſſibility of preſenting himſelf in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54547:44"/> that condition. Thereupon he got leave at the next Houſe to dry his Cloaths, and ſo getting into the Town, he went to the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Palace Royal,</hi> where he met one of his <hi>Nephews</hi> by chance, who was a <hi>Captain</hi> in the <hi>French Army.</hi> His Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew ſeeing him enter, was ſo far from believing him to be his <hi>Uncle,</hi> that he took him for an <hi>Apparition:</hi> For there had lodged the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Perſon</hi> who came from <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurburgh,</hi> who had reported it for <hi>certain News,</hi> which he had ſeen with his own Eyes, that <hi>Mombas</hi>'s Head was cut off. And this <hi>Report</hi> was ſo ſpread about the City, that no body would believe that <hi>Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> was come to <hi>Town.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean while the Duke of <hi>Luxembergh,</hi> who was then chief
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54547:44"/> 
                  <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Utrech,</hi> paus'd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould admit <hi>Mombas</hi> into his preſence or no? For on the one ſide he knew it might be of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to diſcourſe him, as who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtood the <hi>Country;</hi> and on the other ſide he conſider'd that it would be no good <hi>Policy,</hi> to give him a kind <hi>Reception,</hi> which would but convince the World of the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Correſpondence</hi> which he held with the King; which latter thoughts prevailing, he reſolv'd not to ſee him at all, and therefore to thoſe that told it him for great News, that <hi>Mombas</hi> was in Town, he made Anſwer that he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive it, adding withal, that it could never be, that a Man who had born <hi>Arms</hi> againſt the King would put himſelf into his hands.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54547:45"/> Every Body underſtood what the Duke meant, ſo that all Peoples mouths being clos'd after that, there was no more mention made of <hi>Mombas,</hi> than if he never had been.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Mombas</hi> himſelf, when he underſtood, that the Duke of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embergh</hi> would not ſee him, he went to wait upon the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> at <hi>Arnheim,</hi> but that Prince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Politick</hi> as the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> deny'd to ſpeak with <hi>him,</hi> but in private, and that at ſuch an <hi>hour,</hi> when all People elſe were aſleep. Thereupon he ſent the Captain of his Guards for him, about three of the Clock in the Morning, to bring him to his Quarters, where the Prince received him into his Cloſet, wrapt up in his great Leaguer Cloack. There he ſold <hi>Holland</hi> a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54547:45"/> ſecond time, diſcloſing all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of that Republick, or at leaſt as much as he knew before he was Arreſted, and after he had informed the Prince of as much as he deſired to know, he retired to <hi>Collogne,</hi> in expectance there of a Promiſſion to return into <hi>France,</hi> which was one of the wry Faces he was to make, in hopes to wipe off the ſuſpicions which he already lay under. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after he had intimation given him, that he might go and attend the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> who made uſe of him in the taking of <hi>Wordes,</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> quitted, after they had been only once Maſters of it. He it was alſo that brought the <hi>Duke</hi> before this place, when the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> beſeig'd it; ſo that he ſeemed now as deſirous to make
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54547:46"/> his Treacherie publick, as he was before careful to conceal it.</p>
               <p>Now though all this that I have ſaid may ſeem to be rather a Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the War then a keeping cloſe to my Subject, which is to ſet forth the falſhood of <hi>France,</hi> however I beleive it not ſo remote from the matter neither, ſince it ſerves ſo well to recal to Memory the <hi>Idea</hi>'s of ſo many Treacheries and Breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Faith. In a word, though it cannot be denied but that the <hi>French</hi> are ſufficiently couragious, yet we may ſay, that ſhe rather chooſes to joyn Subtlety and Slight to Strength, without which ſhe could never prove ſo Succeſsful in all her Enterprizes; though we muſt needs ſay at the ſame time that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Reaſon of Her Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54547:46"/> is this, that Money coſts Her lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing; for to come now from War to Peace, let us examine how ſhe brought to paſs a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Allies, and whether that Metal did not ſtand her in more ſtead then all the Rhetorick of her Miniſters.</p>
               <p>One of the great Obſtacles of the Peace, was the great difficulty of Reconciling the Intereſts of the Crown of <hi>Sweden,</hi> from the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of thoſe Princes who had any thing to do with it. As for the Crown of <hi>Sweden,</hi> its chiefeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt was this, that as it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a War only for the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> that <hi>France</hi> ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cauſe <hi>Reſtitution</hi> to be made of all thoſe Places, which either the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the Princes of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54547:47"/> 
                  <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> or of the Houſe of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> had taken from it. On the other ſide it was the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> not to hear talk of <hi>Peace,</hi> unleſs they might preſerve all their <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> or at leaſt a good part of them. The difficulty then was to reconcile theſe <hi>oppoſite In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts;</hi> now you ſhall ſee what it was that put this Affair into a fair way, and made it not ſo impoſſible as it ſeem'd to be. It hapned one day, at a <hi>Collation,</hi> that was given by one of the <hi>Three French Miniſters,</hi> who underſtood the <hi>Court Secret,</hi> a <hi>Diſh</hi> of <hi>Olives</hi> was ſet upon the <hi>Table,</hi> which the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor taſting, and liking very well, the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador promis'd to ſend him a <hi>Barril,</hi> which his <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> ſoon after carry'd him. The
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54547:47"/> 
                  <hi>Swediſh</hi> Miniſter was not a little ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd to ſee the <hi>Secretary</hi> of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie</hi> become a <hi>Porter</hi> of <hi>Olives,</hi> but preſently recollecting himſelf he took the <hi>Barril</hi> in his hand, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſomewhat ponderous he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Secretary</hi> what was in the Barril? The <hi>Secretary</hi> made An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that his <hi>Excellency</hi> would ſee when he open'd it; and withal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to open it himſelf, and not to let any body ſee him when he open'd it: Then the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador knew what it meant, and ſo having diſmiſſed the <hi>Secretary,</hi> he open'd the <hi>Barril</hi> which was cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the bottom with <hi>Golden Lewiſſes,</hi> among which he found a little Note wherein theſe words were contain'd, <hi>If You intend that we ſhould ſend you more</hi> Olives, <hi>you muſt let Us have a Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:54547:48"/>
               <p>Now you will ask me how a thing that was carry'd ſo ſecretly on the Miniſter of <hi>France</hi>'s part, as on the Miniſter of <hi>Swedens,</hi> ſhould come to my knowledge, to which I anſwer, how do ſo many ſecrets tranſacted in the Cabinet Councel, come to be known? but I muſt tell ye more then this, that <hi>France</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening afterwards to be at variance with <hi>Sweden,</hi> took no great care to conceal a ſecret, ſince it was of no Importance to her to keep it pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. Rather ſhe was glad of an opportuny to Divulge it, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to raiſe Jealouſies and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts, among the Chief <hi>Grandees</hi> of <hi>Sweden,</hi> where the ſtory is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very bodies Mouth, inſomuch that the Rupture between the two Crowns is attributed to it. In a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54547:48"/> 
                  <hi>word,</hi> though the Homage which the King of <hi>France</hi> demanded of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> for the Dukedom of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> were a thing which that Young Prince took very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly, yet the more nimble Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians beleive, that it would not have been a ſufficient cauſe of a Rupture, had not the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> been exaſperated before, by the Diſadvantageous Peace which <hi>France</hi> had cauſed him to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to; of which it will not be from the purpoſe to ſpeak a word or two, in regard that while I was at <hi>Paris,</hi> I met with few of the <hi>French,</hi> who did not maintain that <hi>Sweden</hi> vvas extremely obliged to <hi>France,</hi> ſince ſhe vvould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hear of any Treaty, till all vvas reſtored that had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54547:49"/> from <hi>Sweden.</hi> But they vvere Ignorant, that in lieu the <hi>Swede</hi> vvas conſtrained to deliver up to the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> ſeveral places in <hi>Pomerania,</hi> in the Dutchie of <hi>Bremen</hi> ſeveral places to the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and ſeveral other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Venden</hi> to the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwick.</hi> But now I am ſpeaking of <hi>Sweden,</hi> I will tell ye how the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Deux Ponts</hi> came to be taken for Her, and under what pretence; the laſt Duke was a Healthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and like to live long, when <hi>France</hi> who lik'd the Country very well, as lying fit for Her, proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted how to get poſſeſſion of it, having not yet bethought her ſelf of the <hi>Knack</hi> of <hi>Dependency,</hi> under pretence of which ſhe has ſince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54547:49"/> ſo many Provinces. Now you muſt underſtand that the <hi>Duke</hi> having no Children, the Dukedom after his Death fell to the Houſe of <hi>Swedland,</hi> though not immediately to the King of <hi>Swedland,</hi> in regard that <hi>Duke Adolphus</hi> pretended to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him as being the next in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity of Blood to the preſent Poſſeſſor. On the other ſide the King <hi>of Sweden</hi> pretended that the <hi>Dukedom</hi> ſhould deſcend to <hi>Him,</hi> as being the Son of the Eldeſt Houſe, which ſeemed a very likely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. For though in ſeveral parts of <hi>Germany</hi> the Cuſtom is ſuch, that the next of Kin to the Deceaſed ſucceeds to his Eſtate, yet in the Electoral Families, eſpecially the <hi>Palatine,</hi> which was then in diſpute, the Uſuage is quite otherwiſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54547:50"/> it were the King of <hi>France,</hi> who was willing to make the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb good, That while two are in diſpute for the Poſſeſſion, there comes a third and carries away the Prize, ſent a conſiderable force to make himſelf Maſter of the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> under pretence nevertheleſs to preſerve it for the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in whoſe favour he had decided the difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Duke <hi>Adolph.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> who was ſtill living, was nothing ſurprized that the <hi>French</hi> had entred his Country, as having often been ſubject to their violences, but he wondred not a little when he underſtood that they came to claim the Succeſſion, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially finding himſelf ſo likely to live, and having no deſire to die ſo
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54547:50"/> ſoon. Nevertheleſs the <hi>French</hi> having taken Poſſeſſion of the place of his Reſidence, he ſaw not only his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> reduced to ſlavery, but himſelf a kind of Priſoner; for in regard the <hi>French</hi> could not chooſe but think that a Prince of ſuch a Noble and Illuſtrious <hi>Birth</hi> would not eaſily condeſcend to live under <hi>Tutelage,</hi> &amp; fearing leaſt that he would call the <hi>Emperor</hi> to his <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> they watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſo narrowly, that he might well be lookt upon rather as a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner then a Freeman.</p>
               <p>However <hi>France,</hi> who was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to make ſure of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> of whom ſhe then ſtood in need (for all this happened during the War) gave him to underſtand that what ſhe had done was only in <hi>kindneſs</hi> to <hi>Him;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Swede</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:54547:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:54547:51"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:54547:52"/> not dreaming but that <hi>France</hi> meant as ſhe ſaid, began to talk of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Governour into the <hi>Dutchy,</hi> but while he offered the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſometimes to the Count of <hi>Carlſon,</hi> his natural Brother in lieu of ſomething that he had taken from <hi>Him,</hi> and ſometimes to a Prince of the Houſe of <hi>Baden,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> ſent thither the Prince Palatine of <hi>Berkenfield,</hi> and reconciled the Prince of <hi>Baden,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Carlſon,</hi> who began to look with an evil aſpect one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, as it is the Cuſtom of two Perſons, that aſpire both to one Command.</p>
               <p>The Peace enſuing ſoon after, <hi>France,</hi> who had no mind to part with ſo toothſom a Morſel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought her ſelf of the Right of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54547:52"/> Dependency, and demanded Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Fealty from the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi> This pretention altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new, extremely ſurprized the <hi>Swediſh</hi> King, but in regard the <hi>Dutchy</hi> lies at a great diſtance from his Dominions, the chiefeſt part of his Miniſters concluded to let it paſs, and not to quarrel with <hi>France,</hi> at what time <hi>France,</hi> who had laid this Rub in the way, only becauſe ſhe would not reſtore what ſhe had got into her Clutches, cauſed Duke <hi>Adolph</hi> to interpoſe himſelf to the end, that according as they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among themſelves, ſhe might remain always in the Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>And thus as ſhe had deſpoiled the Old Duke in his life time, who ended his days for ſorrow remote from his own Territories, ſo ſhe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54547:53"/> ſcruples not to keep from their Rights to other Princes ſtill alive and live like. And it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that without conſidering whether the claim belong to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or Duke <hi>Adolph,</hi> that ſhe will rather chooſe to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render it to the <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Birken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> then to either of the other two, as being loath it ſhould fall into the Hands of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> for fear of enlarging the Power of a Prince, whoſe Friendſhip ſhe has ſo little reaſon to hope, and having the ſame reaſon to be jealous of <hi>Duke Adolph,</hi> whoſe Intereſt it is to keep firmly united to the Head of his own Family.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it cannot but be a great trouble to the Palatine <hi>Houſe,</hi> to ſee ſuch a number of Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54547:53"/> ſubject to <hi>France.</hi> For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, the Perſon upon whom <hi>France</hi> ſhall be pleaſed to confer the <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Deux Ponts,</hi> will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do her Homage, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others are there, who at this day groan under the weight of her Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: The Prince <hi>de la petite Pierre</hi> could ſay ſomething, if the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate example of one of his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did not oblige Him to ſilence. I could ſpeak of the Prince of <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> who for having the ſoul of a Prince, and being willing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve himſelf in that high Dignity where Providence has placed him by Birth, might ſtarve, if his own Subjects had not pity upon him; I ſay that he might ſtarve; nor do I aggravate the matter; for 'tis well known to many others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54547:54"/> my ſelf, that becauſe he would not do Homage to <hi>France,</hi> he has been diſpoſſeſſed of his <hi>Territory,</hi> and lives now in a hired Houſe upon the Alms of his Subjects. 'Tis as vvell knovvn to vvhat a mean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition his Son is reduced. 'Tis vvell <hi>known,</hi> I ſay, that his Father not having vvherevvithal to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him, that rides up and dovvn upon a ſorry Nag vvithout any Train or Attendance, like the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Gentleman in <hi>France,</hi> being at length conſtrain'd to put himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Service</hi> of the <hi>States,</hi> vvho have given him a <hi>Foot Company,</hi> vvhich is all he has to ſubſiſt upon at this Day.</p>
               <p>Some perhaps may ask me, vvhy the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Weldens</hi> carries himſelf ſo untractably conſidering his ovvn
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54547:54"/> vveakneſs, againſt a <hi>Power</hi> ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute? vvhy does he not give vvay to the <hi>Times,</hi> as others do; and in a Word, vvhat difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveen being a <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to the <hi>Emperor</hi> and a <hi>Homager</hi> to the King of <hi>France.</hi> For I knovv theſe are the <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> generally in the <hi>Mouths</hi> not only of thoſe that follovv the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> but alſo of ſeveral others, who cannot but compaſſionate the <hi>Misfortunes</hi> of this <hi>Prince,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to help him: To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that the Prince of <hi>Wildens,</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelf reduced to utmoſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, has ſought an <hi>Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by all-manner of ways; but he could never reſolve to be a <hi>Slave.</hi> In ſhort, when he ſaw that a great many <hi>Princes</hi> of his <hi>Family</hi> had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him the way, he ſent his <hi>Son</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54547:55"/> 
                  <hi>France,</hi> who offer'd on his <hi>Fathers</hi> behalf to do <hi>homage</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he would uſe him like a <hi>Prince</hi> and ſuffer him to enjoy the ſame <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges,</hi> as before the <hi>Change</hi> of his <hi>Affairs:</hi> But the King laugh'd at his <hi>Propoſals,</hi> ſo that the young <hi>Gentleman</hi> was forc'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn as wiſe as he went. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs if I may reflect upon the preſent <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>German Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and what it was formerly, we may eaſily ſee how they abuſe themſelves, that think there is no difference between a <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and a <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to the King of <hi>France:</hi> But I do ill, to ſay a <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to the <hi>Emperor;</hi> for all the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire,</hi> I mean the <hi>Soveraign Princes,</hi> as the <hi>Electors</hi> and ſeveral other great <hi>Houſes,</hi> are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54547:55"/> 
                  <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Empire,</hi> not the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s <hi>Vaſſals.</hi> They are indeed oblig'd to aſſiſt the <hi>Empire,</hi> under <hi>Forfeiture</hi> of their <hi>Privileges</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories,</hi> but they are not oblig'd to aſſiſt the <hi>Emperor,</hi> unleſs he be firſt attack'd. Let us then conclude that this Word <hi>Vaſſal</hi> is not properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> who have <hi>Soveraign Authority</hi> within their own <hi>Dominions,</hi> as much as the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> exerciſes in His own. They have the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> they impoſe <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> at their pleaſure, &amp; laſtly are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for their <hi>Actions</hi> to none but God. Let us conclude, I ſay, that ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> as theſe, who enjoy all the <hi>Marks</hi> of <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> are far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who except that they ſtand with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54547:56"/> their Hats on, when the King gives <hi>Audience</hi> to <hi>Embaſſadors,</hi> are in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe more than other Subjects. It may be ſaid in ſome <hi>Sort,</hi> that they are inferiour to ſome of the Kings Subjects; for the <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> take the <hi>Precedency</hi> of them, and that the <hi>Princes</hi> are oblig'd not to appear at any <hi>Ceremony,</hi> leaſt they ſhould be conſtrain'd to walk after them. Nevertheleſs if we look back to the beginning of the laſt <hi>Century</hi> we ſhall find that among thoſe <hi>Dukes,</hi> there are ſome, whoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> were only <hi>Notaries,</hi> others no more than <hi>Merchants</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi> And we know what the <hi>Deſcendants</hi> from one of theſe great <hi>Families</hi> did not long ſince, to conceal the knowledg of ſuch a mean and ignominious <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction:</hi> We know that they caus'd
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54547:56"/> an <hi>Epitaph</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents</hi> to be eras'd, inſtead of which we find another in the <hi>Celeſtins,</hi> wherein there are as many <hi>Falſhoods</hi> as there were <hi>Truths</hi> in the other.</p>
               <p>And yet it ſo falls out, that <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ancestors</hi> were in the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of <hi>Soveraign Princes,</hi> are at this day forc'd to ſubmit to Men of that low and ſordid <hi>Extraction.</hi> To which I may add, that the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> themſelves are glad to <hi>court</hi> and <hi>fawn</hi> upon Perſons of a much lower and baſer <hi>Extraction</hi> than what I have already mention'd. We know the way to <hi>riſe</hi> in <hi>France</hi> is not to ſtir from the <hi>Anti-chamber</hi> of a <hi>Great Miniſter;</hi> and a Colonel of <hi>Horſe,</hi> whoſe Name I could tell, and one whom every Body knows as well as I, does not diſdain to be
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54547:57"/> a <hi>Buffoon</hi> to one of the <hi>Secretaries</hi> of <hi>State:</hi> For which reaſon he quitted his <hi>Regiment,</hi> for fear, leaſt in time of War, ſome other <hi>Minion</hi> might ſtep into his <hi>Honourable Employment.</hi> 'Tis well known alſo that while Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> ſate at Diner, the greateſt Lords of <hi>France</hi> ſate pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for a Jeſt to make him laugh, and he that had had the beſt <hi>Succeſs,</hi> glory'd in his happy Fortune, as if it had been he who had defended <hi>Vienna</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> Laſtly 'tis well known, and yet a thing which a Man would hardly believe, that Monſieur the <hi>Kings</hi> only <hi>Brother</hi> is oblig'd to have recourſe to them, when he has any particular <hi>Favour</hi> to beg of the <hi>King,</hi> and that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times is forc'd to go without the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54547:57"/> 
                  <hi>Grant</hi> of his <hi>Petition.</hi> I could prove by a <hi>Thouſand Examples</hi> what I here alledg; but it ſhall ſuffice to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only what happen'd about a year or two ſince, upon the ſcore of a <hi>Perſon</hi> whom the <hi>Monſieur</hi> had a kind deſire to put into one of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Farms;</hi> for not being able to obtain what he deſir'd of Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> after many and many <hi>Entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> he was forced himſelf at length to ſpeak to the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To give a little farther proof of the <hi>Tyrannies</hi> of the <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and how the lofty <hi>Princes</hi> are forced to cringe and bow before thoſe <hi>Idols,</hi> there needs no more than to repeat what hapned ſome few days ſince to Monſieur the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> he had beg'd of Monſieur <hi>Segnaly,</hi> the Son of Mr. <hi>Colbert,</hi> the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54547:58"/> of <hi>Purſer</hi> of a Ship, for a Son of one of his <hi>Domeſticks,</hi> which Monſieur <hi>Segnalay</hi> having granted Him with great difficulty, this ſame <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the laſt <hi>Edition</hi> took a <hi>Fancy</hi> ſometime after to diſplace the <hi>Purſer,</hi> pretending him uncapable of the <hi>Imployment.</hi> The <hi>Dauphin</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding this, told Monſieur <hi>Segnaly</hi> that it was his deſire the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might be reſtor'd, and that if he had done amiſs, it was only for his want of years, and that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would undertake the <hi>Young man</hi> ſhould do better for the future. Monſieur <hi>Segnalay</hi> having heard the Prince with that Gravity which he ſo awkardly affects, made anſwer, that the thing was out of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that therefore he muſt ſpeak to the <hi>King:</hi> But Monſieur the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:54547:58"/> not enduring that a Perſon of his <hi>Condition</hi> ſhould ſo unworthily requite the <hi>Honour</hi> which he did him, Schol'd him ſo ſeverely that he ſoon humbled his vain-glorious <hi>Pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then conclude from hence that it is a great <hi>Misfortune</hi> for a Prince to be born a <hi>Subject</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and a great <hi>Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> in him that is free to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under the <hi>Yoak.</hi> Ask the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> who is only his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> how he likes his <hi>Neighbourhood,</hi> and I am ſure he will tell you, there is no difference from being a <hi>Subject</hi> and a Neighbour. If he ſpeaks like a Prince, they ſpeak to him like Maſters, and if he intends that <hi>France</hi> ſhould let him be at quiet, He muſt ſubmit to all her Demands. Let us ask him whether he hath any
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54547:59"/> Subjects that are <hi>Faithful</hi> to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many <hi>Subjects</hi> as are obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to him? and whether <hi>France</hi> have not quite debauch'd their <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance?</hi> Laſtly let us ask him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he dares complain, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day he finds one Corner or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Territories lopt off from his Subjection, and whither they do not tell him on the other ſide, that he is happy to be under the Protection of ſo great a Potentate? Let us now viſit the Courts of the other Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſee what paſſes there, before we make any Reflection upon the Princes of <hi>France.</hi> What ſhall we ſay of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Electors; of which the one ſells his Country by the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of <hi>her Emiſſaries;</hi> the other ſuffers her ſelf to be ſcar'd by her <hi>Emiſſaries:</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:54547:59"/> &amp; the other is ſo obedient to her <hi>Will</hi> as if the ſame Intereſt actuated in all. Yet at the ſame time let us confeſs, that this is not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſort of Violence, for who queſtions the various Tricks and gins that are made uſe of daily to ſeparate 'em from their real Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts? To ſome they pretend, that the moſt part of their Territories are Dependencies upon the Crown, and that if they do not uſe all means to Captivate the Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, he will no longer ſuffer 'em to enjoy that to which they have no Right at all; ſo that while he deprives them of the true Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of Soveraign, which is to be independent in their Authority, he endeavours to inſinuate the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that their dependance upon <hi>France</hi> is the only way to ſupport
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54547:60"/> their Dominion. To others he cries, that they have nothing to do but to conſider his <hi>Power,</hi> &amp; from thence to aſſure themſelves that they have no other hopes but in <hi>Him;</hi> and while he feeds them with theſe fair <hi>Hopes,</hi> he boys up the <hi>People</hi> in their <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc,</hi> to the end the Soveraigns may always ſtanding in need of him, to ſuppreſs their mutinies. It may well be thought that I ſpeak of <hi>Liege,</hi> where <hi>France</hi> holds her <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van</hi> contrary to the Faith of <hi>Treaties,</hi> and where the <hi>Diſſentions</hi> between the People and their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> make her as abſolutely Miſtreſs of the City, as if it belonged ſolely to <hi>Her;</hi> for who is ſo blind as not to ſee through her Politicks upon this occaſion? For being in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual fear, leaſt Monſieur of <hi>Cologne</hi> ſhould at length open his Eyes, ſhe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54547:60"/> reſolves to have a Remedy ready againſt all manner of Accidents. And therefore as ſhe maintained the People of <hi>Meſſina</hi> in their Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo will ſhe ſupport the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Liege</hi> in all their Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices, ſhould <hi>Monſieur</hi> of <hi>Cologne</hi> at any time bethink himſelf of re-aſſuming his Lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty. For indeed if this were not the Intention of <hi>France,</hi> what could hinder <hi>Monſieur Cologne</hi> at this day, from reducing to Obedience a City which is open on all ſides, without Fortifications or any Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. It were then to be wiſhed that he would come again to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and conſider that his Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> has only ſerv'd to draw upon him the hatred of his People, and the utter Ruin of his Country
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54547:61"/> for not to mention the Imperial-Armies, who have been Conſtrained to feed upon his Country, we ſee How he has been treated himſelf, by thoſe in whom he has put all his hopes and confidence. Who can be Ignorant of the Horrible Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions which <hi>France</hi> has Levied upon his Subjects, the General De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of his <hi>Territory,</hi> the Sacking and Plundering of his <hi>Towns,</hi> and the Deſtruction of his <hi>Citadels</hi> and other Stately <hi>Buildings?</hi> Who can be Ignorant of what Happened at the <hi>Hay,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> not contented, to have <hi>Tyranniz'd</hi> o're the <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> threw the <hi>Caſtle</hi> to the <hi>Ground,</hi> and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd one of the <hi>Nobleſt Bridges</hi> upon the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> by which meanes that <hi>City</hi> finds her ſelf <hi>depriv'd</hi> of all her chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt &amp; moſt conſiderable <hi>advantages</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:54547:61"/> for having admitted them within her Walls. But let us go on to the other Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſee whether they have any more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to boaſt of the <hi>French</hi> kindneſſes.</p>
               <p>I could Epitomize all at once what I have to ſay to this point, by only declaring what happened but lately to the King of <hi>Danemark.</hi> For as it may be eaſie for others to judge what they are to expect, by the carriage of the <hi>French</hi> toward their Allies, therefore in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that might ſuffice to prove the <hi>Violence</hi> of her Proceedings, and how ſhe goes about to make her ſelf Miſtreſs of the whole World. But in regard there are ſeveral that would be glad to ſee what pretty <hi>Courſes</hi> ſhe takes to bring about her <hi>Deſigns,</hi> I will give you a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:54547:62"/> of her <hi>Maxims</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no Body can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the <hi>Marriage</hi> of the <hi>Dauphin</hi> with the <hi>Dauphineſs.</hi> The great <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuation</hi> which Monſieur of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the great <hi>Sway</hi> which he carries in the <hi>Empire,</hi> as well by reaſon of the <hi>Extent</hi> of his <hi>Dominions,</hi> as alſo by reaſon of their <hi>Situation,</hi> caus'd him to be courted of all hands du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the laſt War, as He who brought a great Acceſſion of <hi>Strength</hi> to the ſide for which he ſhould declare. The King of <hi>France</hi> being careful of loſing ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, dayly made him a <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> advantageous <hi>Propoſitions</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf in his <hi>Intereſts.</hi> On the other ſide the <hi>Emperor</hi> was no leſs ſedulous to gain him to his <hi>Party.</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:54547:62"/> So that the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Power by the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that were made to him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to hear both, and to fix where he could make his beſt Markets.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Emperor</hi> he only offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a League Offenſive and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive againſt <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſigns he laid before him, beleiving that enough to bring him over to the <hi>German</hi> Intereſt: But <hi>Bavaria</hi> being in hopes of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more advantageous, liſtened more willingly to the propoſitions of <hi>France,</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make as acceptible as poſſibly they could. In ſhort too many politick Arguments, which might have been more prevalent at ſome other time, but now of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no effect, they added moſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:54547:63"/> magnificent Preſents, which they were careful to renew from time to time; ſo that <hi>Princes</hi> being wrought upon many times by ſuch kind of <hi>Temptations</hi> as well as other Perſons, the Duke began to be more and more enclined to <hi>France.</hi> Madam of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> whom the King had formerly had ſome thoughts to have married, and who was not a little troubled that ſhe had miſſed the preferment, hoping to advance her Daughter to the <hi>Throne</hi> which ſhe had failed off, preſt her <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> with all her might to the <hi>French</hi> Alliance, provided he made ſure of the Advancement of his <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who could not expect a more advantageous match in all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was it long before the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>France</hi> diſcovered what
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54547:63"/> had paſſed in the Duke of <hi>Bavarias</hi> Cabinet, and therefore beleiving it would be more kindly taken to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Duke, by propoſing the Match before the Duke offered it himſelf, they declared that they had orders from their Maſter to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe him about it; and this they alſo made known to Madam of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> who was ready to leap out of her skin for joy. After this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition thus made, the Emperors Miniſters were no longer minded, and nothing was diſcourſed of but the future Alliance, which was the Foundation of the enſuing Treaty between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by which the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to remain <hi>Neuter,</hi> which was all that <hi>France</hi> deſir'd. For in regard that <hi>Bavaria</hi> had a powerful <hi>Army</hi> on <hi>foot,</hi> &amp; that he was <hi>reſolved</hi> to ſtand <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:54547:64"/> ſo long at the <hi>War</hi> endured, <hi>France</hi> conjectured, and that not without reaſon, that the Emperor would be awed by his potent ſtrength, which would be as beneficial to <hi>France,</hi> as if the Duke acted openly. And by the Event it appeared that thoſe <hi>Conjectures</hi> were not ill groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But not to make a repetition of things known to every body; it will ſuffice to ſay, that this Treaty continued till the Treaty of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen,</hi> and that the Mariage of <hi>Madamoiſelle</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> was ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>conſummated,</hi> there being at that time no Princes in <hi>Europe</hi> unmarried, either of a nobler <hi>Family,</hi> or endow'd with more Princely Qualities.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>France</hi> thought her ſelf ſecure of the Houſe of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> but the Duke and Dutches dying, and the <hi>Dukedom</hi> falling into the <hi>Hands</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:54547:64"/> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> more clear ſighted than his Father and Mother, <hi>France</hi> finding he did not ſtand ſo right for their Turn, made it their buſineſs to faſten him by ſome new Ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. To this purpoſe, becauſe their is nothing ſooner tempts a young Prince then Beauty, chiefly when it is accompanied by great Merit, the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> ſo ordered it, that they whom they had gained to their Party, ſhould fill his Ears with their diſcourſes of <hi>Madam Blois,</hi> the Kings natural Daughter, who appearing ſo love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in her tender Age, promiſed to be in a ſhort time, one of the moſt charming Perſons in the World. <hi>Monſieur</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> perceiving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf perhaps ſmitten with what was imprinted every hour in his mind,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54547:65"/> or elſe out of <hi>Curioſity</hi> to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fame did not too much exalt the <hi>Beautys</hi> of that Lady, ſeem'd to intimate as if he ſhould not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſee her <hi>Picture.</hi> Of which his moſt <hi>faithful Friends,</hi> and thoſe that were more jealous of his <hi>Honor</hi> being inform'd, they made him ſo effectually ſenſible of the Snares that were ſpread for his <hi>Youth,</hi> that the Prince recollecting his <hi>Thoughts,</hi> began to be <hi>aſham'd</hi> of what <hi>perhaps</hi> he had only done out of <hi>Curioſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time ſeveral <hi>Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of Madam <hi>de Blois</hi> were ſent from <hi>France,</hi> but the <hi>Ministers</hi> of that <hi>Crown,</hi> perceiving that the <hi>Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimacy</hi> of her <hi>Birth,</hi> defaced all the Impreſſions that her <hi>Beauty</hi> could make, gave over the <hi>Deſign</hi> of that <hi>Match,</hi> of which they had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:54547:65"/> ſuch hopes a little before.</p>
               <p>After this they propoſed another Match to the <hi>Bavarian,</hi> which was certainly much more ſuitable: And that was between the <hi>Duke</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle</hi> the Queen of <hi>Spains</hi> Siſter, and Daughter to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans.</hi> But the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Miniſters, who had diverted his firſt Paſſions, eaſily beat him off from this, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him that it was only a <hi>ſnare</hi> to keep him from allying with the <hi>Emperor,</hi> whoſe Daughter he might be in hopes to marry, which would not be only a greater advantage to him, but more neceſſary and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for his Intereſts. That it behov'd him to have his Eyes open and to look upon the <hi>Deſigns</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which were only to ruine the <hi>Emperor</hi> and the <hi>Empire.</hi> That
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54547:66"/> it was true ſhe fed him from time to time with fair <hi>Fancies,</hi> as that ſhe would cauſe him to be <hi>Elected King</hi> of the <hi>Romans;</hi> but that the bottom of her <hi>Deſign</hi> was only to diſunite the <hi>Princes</hi> one from another, that when the <hi>Election</hi> ſhould happen, ſhe might be the better able to carve for her ſelf, what ſhe offer'd to others. That it was not his <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> to deſire a <hi>Neighbourhood</hi> ſo dreadful to all that had been ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate to be her <hi>Neighbours;</hi> which was no <hi>Reproach</hi> or <hi>Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and that there needed no more than the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of their <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to make others ſenſible of the danger of <hi>Falling</hi> into the like.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſage <hi>Councels,</hi> made that <hi>Impreſſion</hi> which might well be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected upon the mind of a Prince,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54547:66"/> who lov'd <hi>Honour</hi> and ſcorn'd to ſtoop under <hi>Subjection.</hi> On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing theſe <hi>Proceedings,</hi> were ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd at the Dukes <hi>Refuſal</hi> of their propounded Match; that they had the <hi>Inſolence</hi> to tell him, that if the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> had married <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammoiſelle de Blois,</hi> it had been no Diſparagement to him. That there was no doubt but that Princes as puiſſant as himſelf would deſire her in <hi>Marriage,</hi> who were like to go without her for all that; and that the King was ſufficiently potent to <hi>Revenge</hi> one day the <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> which he had put upon his <hi>Alliance.</hi> Theſe <hi>Rhodomontadoes</hi> gave the Duke ſufficiently to underſtand, how <hi>France</hi> at firſt wound her ſelf in by ſoftneſs and mildneſs, but that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:54547:67"/> ſhe was ſtill for force where that fail'd. But theſe Proceedings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to no other end then to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Duke the farther off from the <hi>French,</hi> he preſently treated with the <hi>Emperor,</hi> with whom he might be certain to find more Honour, and more Security.</p>
               <p>Nor has the Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> more reaſon to applaud the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>France,</hi> who finding that Prince faſt link'd to the true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of <hi>Germany,</hi> not ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be fed with her empty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, has raiſed him up ſeveral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies both at home and abroad, and uſed all imaginable tricks to ſet him at variance with the <hi>Princes</hi> of his <hi>Family,</hi> but not being <hi>able</hi> to bring her deſigns to paſs: She had been tampering with the <hi>Princes</hi> his <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:54547:67"/> which occaſioned thoſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies ſo prudently already laid aſleep by the Emperor.</p>
               <p>As for the Marquiſs of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and the King of <hi>Danemark,</hi> I know nothing that could beget a greater Averſion to <hi>France,</hi> then her behaviour towards them. For if we look upon the manner how ſhe came to intrude her ſelf into their <hi>Confidence,</hi> we ſhall find that ſhe has left no <hi>Tricks</hi> unplaid to bring it to paſs, but after ſhe had got her Ends, there was no ſort of <hi>Severity</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> which ſhe did not exerciſe to their <hi>Dammage.</hi> The <hi>Propoſitions</hi> are well known; which were made by the Count <hi>de Roy,</hi> upon his <hi>Arrival</hi> in the <hi>North.</hi> 'Tis well known, I ſay, that he demanded of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Danemark,</hi> in the name of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54547:68"/> 
                  <hi>King</hi> his Maſter, that he might have a ſhare in the <hi>Disburſement</hi> of the Money which he received from Him, adding withal, that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was waſted to little purpoſe: He demanded alſo little leſs of the Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh;</hi> yet fearing to provoke thoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> jealous of their Honours, by ſuch kind of harſh Complements, he kept his <hi>Penſioners,</hi> or elſe certain <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ſtill at their Elbows to mollifie and ſweeten thoſe ſevere Pieces of <hi>Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> ſo that thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, as I may ſay, between hope and fear, knew not what to reſolve upon. But let us admire the <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> of that Crown, which draws it's <hi>Advantages</hi> from all things, even from thoſe things that ſeem to be <hi>contrary</hi> and <hi>prejudicial</hi> to it's <hi>Intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:54547:68"/>
               <p>Every one knows how Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>de Bricquant</hi> was proſecuted; who after he had been a long time in the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> for being ſtedfaſt to his Principles, was at length for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly his <hi>Country,</hi> having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to hope from his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>France;</hi> where he had never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſpent all his youthful years: but ſo ſoon as <hi>France</hi> underſtood, that he was gone to <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and that he was received by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, her Malice was not only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed of a ſuddain, but ſhe would needs Recommend him to that Prince, not immediately as from her ſelf, for that would have been ſuſpicious; but indirectly by the means of her Generals, ſo that this ſame Recommendation accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the merit of the Perſon,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:54547:69"/> got him in a ſhort time a Regiment of Horſe with the Government of <hi>Weſel;</hi> and of this Perſon it is that ſhe makes uſe, but cunningly and ſlily to obtain her deſires; For tho he does not appear to be entruſted with the ſecret, but that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he ſtill complains of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and hard uſage in <hi>France,</hi> he knows how to give the blow when Opportunity ſerves, a Blow ſo much the more dangerous, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a kind and unſuſpected Hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boisdavid,</hi> who was conſtrained to fly <hi>France,</hi> where he was a <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadier</hi> and Colonel of Foot, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving duell'd Monſieur <hi>d'Aubijoux,</hi> underſtood the way to regain her <hi>Favour</hi> by managing her <hi>Intereſts</hi> in the Court of <hi>Zell,</hi> where he was
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:54547:69"/> advantageouſly preferr'd, ſo that nothing there paſs'd of which Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Louvois</hi> was not advertis'd from time to time. And that which was moſt extraordinary was this, that though there be no Mercy for thoſe who are accus'd of the ſame Crime that he was, he forbears not to make a Journey ſometimes to <hi>Paris,</hi> whether it be upon his own occaſions, or which is moſt likely to confer with Monſieur <hi>de St. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vange,</hi> about ſuch things as he dares not commit to Writing.</p>
               <p>All the Courts of the other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are in the ſame manner ſtuft ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with banniſh'd or <hi>Malecontented French.</hi> But at the ſame time thoſe Princes give 'em Entertainment, if it may not be ſaid that they receive Serpents into their Boſoms, at leaſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54547:70"/> we may ſay, that they are to be very wary how they eaſily truſt 'em with their Secrets. For beſides that the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Nation carrys them to inſinuate themſelves into all manner of buſineſs, they rarely forget their Fidelity to their Prince, ſo that it is a great piece of <hi>Imprudence</hi> to confide in their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus diſcourſed of the Misfortunes daily attending thoſe Princes who are <hi>Neighbours</hi> to <hi>France</hi> or that are in any ſort of <hi>Amity</hi> with Her, let us now ſee in what a <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> they are, who are envellop'd by her in her <hi>Claims</hi> of Dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. I will ſay nothing of the Prince of <hi>Petite Pierre,</hi> or of <hi>Weldens,</hi> of whom we have ſpoken ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently already, but I will mention
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:54547:70"/> ſomething of the Prince of <hi>Baden,</hi> who no ſooner came to be in the number of Her Subjects, but he was conſtrained to give a large <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to his Wife, who left him a long time ſince, with a reſolution never to Cohabit with him any more. He might ſhew himſelf ready as he did, to take her home again, but there was no regard had to Reaſons, and the firſt thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon him was to aſcertain Her a revenue, where he could not come to Finger it. I paſs over in ſilence the Tyranny which She Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes over other Princes of leſs repute; for ſince the Princes of the Sovereign Families, are no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpared then as I have related, there is no likelihood that the reſt ſhould fare any better. It would
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:54547:71"/> be tedious to recount what they daily ſuffer from thoſe Petty <hi>Tyrants,</hi> who, of great Miniſters <hi>Lacquies,</hi> becoming <hi>Commiſſaries,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary <hi>Intendants,</hi> aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Soveraign Authority. Nor are they contented to deprive theſe Princes of their <hi>Honour,</hi> but of their <hi>Eſtates.</hi> How many ſuits do they commence againſt them for the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> of <hi>Limits,</hi> and ſeveral other ſlight occaſions; inſomuch that thoſe Princes, who but lately had the Power of Life and Death over their Subjects, are now forced to go and anſwer their ſuits at the <hi>Bar,</hi> and frequently looſe their Cauſes. For it is a Maxim of <hi>France</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Vaſſals againſt their <hi>Lords,</hi> well knowing, that as long as they have the People of their ſide, the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:54547:71"/> Princes and Gentry are not to be feared at all, who can do little with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the People, ſo that Her Intereſt ſweys Her beyond all manner of Juſtice, provided ſhe can thereby Eſtabliſh her Dominion, or rather her abſolute Tyranny.</p>
               <p>If we paſs from hence to her u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the meaner Gentry, how many may we find ruin'd by their Garriſons: For ſhe does not ſtop at ordinary Forms to eſtabliſh her <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,</hi> though it be the Law to ſeize the Lands only of thoſe that refuſe Homage and Fealty, how many has ſhe nevertheleſs impriſoned, to the end that by detaining at the ſame time, both their Perſons and their Eſtates, neceſſity may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them to an abſolute Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to her Pleaſure? But the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:54547:72"/> of her Tyranny and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice was her ſeverity to the <hi>Baron de L'Evenop,</hi> a Gentleman of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and of a Family that once ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>Sweden</hi> with a Queen. For after <hi>France</hi> had received his Fealty and Homage, ſhe diſpoſſeſſed him of his demeans, no perſon being able to ſay for what reaſon, nor could ſhe ever give any her ſelf, but her own covetous thirſt after other Peoples Eſtates.</p>
               <p>There is no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> who has not had a taſte of her violences: who though they are ſufficiently powerful to repreſs her <hi>Inſolence,</hi> yet ſuch is their blindneſs, that inſtead of uniting together for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, one would think they had conſpir'd by their Diſunion to ſurrender into her hands the <hi>Empire</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:54547:72"/> of the World. They know that ſhe is in League with the <hi>Turk</hi> to harraſs <hi>Germany,</hi> one on one ſide, and the other on the other ſide, and yet they will not unite to deſtroy an Enemy that ſeeks to reduce them to utter Slavery.</p>
               <p>And now ſince I have mention'd this <hi>Allyance</hi> with the <hi>Turk,</hi> it may not be amiſs to convince thoſe who have hitherto ſeem'd to make ſome queſtion of the Truth of it, and that by one <hi>Circumſtance</hi> againſt which there is no <hi>Reply.</hi> Every one knows the vigorous <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> which the Count of <hi>Starenbergh</hi> Governour of <hi>Vienna</hi> made againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi> So that the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> after the loſs of an <hi>Infinite Number</hi> of his Men, would have raiſed the Siege, if he could have done it with <hi>Honour.</hi> To which
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:54547:73"/> purpoſe he ſent back Count <hi>Albert Caprara,</hi> who was Embaſſador at the <hi>Emperors Court,</hi> whom he would never permit to return before that, to make him ſome <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> much more reaſonable than thoſe which he had propoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: But the Marquiſs of <hi>Seppeville</hi> who attended the <hi>Emperor</hi> from the King of <hi>France,</hi> being advertis'd thereof, diſpatch'd a <hi>Currier</hi> to his Maſter to give him advice of it; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>Information France</hi> ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> to lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him the <hi>Diſhonour</hi> it would be to his <hi>Reputation,</hi> to raiſe the <hi>Siege</hi> ſo ignominiouſly after had loſt ſuch a Number of Men: Therefore that he would enter <hi>Flanders</hi> to conſtrain the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Rhine</hi> to recal their <hi>Succours,</hi> which they had ſent to the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:54547:73"/> 
                  <hi>Emperor;</hi> by which <hi>Diverſion</hi> he might ſoon accompliſh his <hi>Deſign.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Seppeville</hi>'s Currier arriv'd at <hi>Fountain Bleau</hi> the 22d. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> between <hi>eight</hi> and <hi>nine</hi> of the Clock in the Morning. The Perſon who was diſpatch'd to the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> or to Monſieur <hi>Seppeville,</hi> which is the ſame thing, went away at <hi>one</hi> of the Clock in the <hi>Afternoon;</hi> and the ſame <hi>Afternoon</hi> they did not only noiſe abroad their <hi>Intentions</hi> of inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Flanders,</hi> but orders were alſo given out in order thereto; ſo that the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> not queſtioning but that the <hi>French</hi> would keep their words this time more punctually than they had done before, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſeige, and it is very probable that he would never have raiſed it, had he not been conſtrained to it,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:54547:74"/> till he had been Maſter of the Town. Which having brought me to ſpeak of <hi>France</hi>'s breach of <hi>Faith</hi> to the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> it will not be amiſs to tell the cauſe of it. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that by a <hi>Private Treaty</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>France</hi> and the Ottoman <hi>Port,</hi> for which <hi>Teckeley</hi> became ſecurity, and one whoſe name was <hi>Bohan</hi> the Inſtrument that managed the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>France</hi> was obliged to attach the Empire upon the ſide next the <hi>Rhine,</hi> at what time the <hi>Ottoman</hi> was to invade <hi>Hungary.</hi> To which purpoſe the King of <hi>France</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready advanced upon the <hi>Frontiers;</hi> but finding that the <hi>Turks</hi> having made ſuch a proſperous Progreſs at the beginning, that he made no queſtion but that they would carry <hi>Vienna,</hi> where they had already
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:54547:74"/> planted their ſeige, had put all <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> into ſuch a Conſternation, that all the Princes of the Empire gave themſelves for loſt, he ſtopped his March neither out of Moderation nor Chriſtianity; but fearing to looſe the good opinions of the Princes, imagining that in the condition to which they were reduced, they would be conſtrained to fly to him for Succour. And therefore think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf cock ſure of the <hi>Empire,</hi> he would not carry Terror and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation into a place which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſo ſoon to command; which was the reaſon that he rather ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Spain</hi> than the <hi>Empire.</hi> For he was always in hopes, that if the <hi>Turks</hi> got poſſeſſion of <hi>Vienna,</hi> there was not any but himſelf that could oppoſe ſo formidable a Power, as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:54547:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> if the Princes of the <hi>Empire</hi> would not rather have choſen to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Tributary to the <hi>Turk,</hi> then to have ſubmitted to the Yoak of <hi>French</hi> ſlavery. In a word, not to ſpeak any more of Her Tyranny, which is incomparably more intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable than <hi>Pagan</hi> Servitude, may we not probably believe that ſhe will exerciſe the ſame ſevery over their Conſcience, not permitting the publick worſhip of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as among the <hi>Heathens</hi> you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear of thoſe terrible Edicts, that commanded the demoliſhing of Churches, nor of Souldiers that only ſerve for Hangmen and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners, to thoſe that aſſembled together upon their Ruins, to ſing Praiſes to their Creator.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:54547:75"/>
               <p>But though it be an eaſie thing, at leaſt as I imagine to inculcate a horrour and dread of this unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Domination, it is not ſo eaſie to teach the means to avoid it; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, as I have already ſaid, that all the Princes of the <hi>Empire</hi> ſeem to conſpire to lay poor ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated <hi>Germany</hi> in Fetters, at Her Feet. For is it not a thing that would move both Pity and Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation at the ſame time, to ſee that at a time when every one ſhould labour their utmoſt, to withſtand ſuch an encroaching Violence, they daily ſtrive to enlarge and ſupport her Power? For what may they be ſaid to think, who went about to Elect the Biſhop of <hi>Cologne,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Straſburgh</hi> to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter?</hi> do they not know that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:54547:76"/> they are both entirely devoted to the Intereſt of <hi>France?</hi> Or if <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> of <hi>Cologne</hi> ſhould chance to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his Eyes, <hi>Monſieur</hi> of <hi>Straſburgh</hi> has ſuch an Aſcendant over him; that he would ſtill prevail over him to continue in his <hi>Blindneſs?</hi> Do they not know, that if <hi>Monſieur</hi> of <hi>Cologne</hi> be a lover of <hi>Peace, Monſieur</hi> of <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> affects nothing ſo much as <hi>War?</hi> Do they not know, that it was by the perſwaſions of the <hi>Deceaſed Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> of <hi>Cologne,</hi> and the defunct Biſhop of <hi>Straſburgh,</hi> that <hi>France</hi> ſo furiouſly invaded the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; and that to increaſe the Power of their Succeſſors, no leſs paſſionately enclined to enſlave <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> they have the ſame Repute, the ſame Inclinations, the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns with the Deceaſed? as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame Blood in their Veins,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:54547:76"/> and the ſame Souls in their Bodies? And yet when they ſaw into what a Precipice the <hi>Deceaſed</hi> had plung'd all <hi>Germany,</hi> as if they had quite forgot what was paſt, they would needs put the ſame Power into the Hands of their <hi>Nephews</hi> to Execute thoſe things, which the Uncles had only in their Wills to do. The one already has ſurrendred the Capital City of his Biſhoprick into the Hands of the <hi>French;</hi> and they would have the other to deliver up the reſt of <hi>Germany,</hi> which is already ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently captivated by their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. They would in a word tie up the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Hands, by the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinity of a new Enemy, and by that means enchain the reſt of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> whoſe <hi>hopes</hi> depend upon 'em.</p>
               <p>But let us conclude a diſcourſe which 'tis to be feared will do but
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:54547:77"/> little good, in regard that all the World is of that diſpoſition; as not to love to be too nakedly told the Truth. So that as much as <hi>France</hi> may be offended with me for diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering her Maxims and Policies, as much will others bear me ill will for reprehending their Weakneſs and Blindneſs. Yet I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear from ſaying this, with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of what ever they may think, that they make themſelves Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices in all the <hi>Enterprizes</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> if they do not put an end to thoſe differences that have ſo long kept them in Diſ-union. For what can we ſay more? For one ſtrives to invade <hi>Lubec,</hi> another <hi>Pomeraenia,</hi> others make head againſt them, while on the other ſide a Potent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy minds nothing more then to bring them altogether under his
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:54547:77"/> ſubjection. They will not permit one Neighbour to grow more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful then another, but the never conſider that there is an Enemy approaching, who not contented to have encreaſed his Dominions by large Conqueſts, will never be ſatisfied with being no more then their Neighbour, agreeable to what is ſaid by the <hi>Author</hi> of a <hi>late Paſquil</hi> upon the preſent condition of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> For when he ſpeaks of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> he brings them in ſaying, That they will not have the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> Reign over them; to which anſwer is made, That they <hi>Act</hi> like <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Blindmen;</hi> they are afraid leſt the <hi>Dog</hi> ſhould bite 'em, but ne'r mind the <hi>Wolf</hi> who is ready to devour 'em. Thus the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes perceive that <hi>Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:54547:78"/> would fain joyn <hi>Hamborough</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck</hi> to the <hi>Crown;</hi> but they do not ſee that <hi>France</hi> will not only joyn to her <hi>Crown,</hi> not only both thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but their own <hi>Territories</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they do not <hi>Unite</hi> to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Her. They find that the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> has a deſign upon <hi>Pomerania,</hi> from whence he believes himſelf Excluded <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but they do not obſerve, that while they oppoſe the Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>His Dominion,</hi> another en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes his Power ſo faſt, that they run the hazard of being totally ſwallowed up by his Oppreſſion. What remedy then againſt ſo many Miſchiefs, but to forget the <hi>Old Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,</hi> and to begin a new one. But firſt it behoves 'em to baniſh from <hi>their Councils</hi> thoſe <hi>Treacherous Souls,</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:54547:78"/> who having crept into the favour of their Princes, reward 'em with continual Treaſons for their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. They muſt give ear to none but their old Servants, whoſe Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they have ſo often experienc'd that it would be an injury to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect 'em. For in the age we live in, we ought to diſtruſt all the World, conſidering the general Corruption that ſhews it ſelf every day; For had not <hi>Straſburgh</hi> been free to this day, had ſhe had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other then Perſons of Fidelity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her Boſom? But let us here I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech ye conſider and admire the differences between the Services that <hi>France</hi> receives from her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and that which other States receive from theirs, which are in the ſervice of <hi>France.</hi> I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:54547:79"/> ye before, how <hi>Boisdavid</hi> and <hi>Brignant</hi> baniſh'd and proſcrib'd as they are, notwithſtanding ſerve as ſpies, the one in the Court of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> the other in the Court of <hi>Zell.</hi> I find I have ſhewed ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that their Fidelity ought to have been little Credited by thoſe Princes; but now let us on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide ſee why the Fidelity of Count <hi>Hasfield,</hi> born a Subject to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſhould be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by the Prince his Maſter.</p>
               <p>Every own knows his Birth, and it would be ſuperfluous to ſpeak of it here, were it not to tell ye, that his Father being a <hi>French Man,</hi> and his Mother a <hi>French Woman,</hi> 'tis no wonder he retains the nature of a <hi>French Man</hi> himſelf. Nevertheleſs there is this to be ſaid againſt him,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:54547:79"/> that after he had been born in <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and raiſed from nothing by the favour of the King, all other <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations</hi> ought to have given place; for that, what was a Vertue in his Father was a Crime in Him. Now who could ever dream without having an enmity to his perſon, that while <hi>France</hi> treats the King his Maſter after ſo gentile a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that he ſhould conſpire the ſlavery of <hi>Germany?</hi> and yet was it not he that made ſo many Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to <hi>Straſburgh,</hi> where he had more advantage to treat then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by reaſon of his familiarity with the Language, and for that he was leaſt ſuſpected? Is not this he that kept ſo many Cabals in <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</hi> where he knew the Great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages were diſcontented, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:54547:80"/> that the King has taken from them ſundry great profits, which they enjoyed rather by the Profuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then Liberality of his <hi>Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors?</hi> I only call the great Perſons to Witneſs theſe things, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not likewiſe true, that at a drinking bout, where there were about ſeven or eight in Company, one of the Gang ſaid to the reſt, that if <hi>Hasfield</hi> were to be belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they would ſoon make a <hi>Tecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> among themſelves. However it be, he cannot ſay but that <hi>France</hi> has recompenc'd him very well for his good Service. For beſides that he receives very conſiderable Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and large Preſents, She has advanced all his Family: He has two Brothers, of which the one is ſuddainly to be a Biſhop, the other
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:54547:80"/> an Abbot, the King having promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, who never fails of his Word, unleſs it be that which he and his Miniſters call <hi>Word of State.</hi> He has alſo two other Brothers, of which the one is at <hi>Hamborough,</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd by the King of <hi>France,</hi> the worthy Brother of Monſieur <hi>Has<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> that is to ſay, one as ready as himſelf to ſell <hi>Germany,</hi> if it were in his Power, and the other in <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> who gives Intelligence of all that paſſes there; beſides all thoſe other Noble Gentlemen there, the Son of Monſieur <hi>Bidal</hi> a Merchant, the famous Bankrupt whom <hi>Bolleau</hi> has not failed to paint forth in his Satyrs, though he was lately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by an expreſs order of the <hi>Court,</hi> to leave that paſſage out in in his next <hi>Edition.</hi> For Monſieur
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:54547:81"/> 
                  <hi>Hasfield</hi> performing ſo many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Exploits, to render his Name immortal, it is but juſt to deface the Monuments of his Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>The way then to prevent ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Abuſes, is to imitate the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>France</hi> at this day; for ſhe does not only confiſcate the Goods of ſuch as betake themſelves to the Service of other Princes, but ſhe always prohibits them under ſtrict Penalties and corporal puniſhment, to go abroad. Nevertheleſs if ſhe ſhews her ſelf indulgent to any, it is eaſily thence to be infer'd; they only ſerve as ſpies in the Courts of thoſe Princes that employ them; which is too ſerious a Truth.</p>
               <p>Let us then conclude, that ſo long as there is no order taken to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:54547:81"/> prevent theſe abuſes, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we ſhould ever proſper; but that <hi>France</hi> on the other ſide will have all the Advantages ſhe can deſire. For how is it poſſible that any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of ours ſhould be <hi>Crown'd</hi> with happy Succeſs, of which the <hi>Enemy</hi> has <hi>Intelligence</hi> long before it be put in Execution. To this let us add, that if it will not ſuffice for a Prince to diſtruſt his own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or to change them, let him be himſelf his own <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as one that may be aſſur'd that if there be one Perſon in his <hi>Council</hi> who is <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation-proof,</hi> there are hundreds that cannot reſiſt the <hi>Golden Charms.</hi> And let him conſider that if he himſelf as frequently now adays it happens will ſuffer himſelf to be purchaſed by him that offers moſt, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:54547:82"/> may well do the ſame, who have more need of Money then he has.</p>
               <p>There might be ſomething alſo ſaid touching the Remedy to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied for prevention of theſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, with which we find our ſelves at this day overwhelm'd. But in regard I can ſay no more then what other People have ſaid before me, I had rather be ſilent, then to make too many repetitions in vain, and for the moſt part ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Speculative then Real. For when I conſider what I have read in ſo many Authors, and heard in ſo many places, that it behoves all the Proteſtants to unite together, ſince the Catholicks are ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to oppoſe themſelves againſt the common Ruin, may not I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:54547:82"/> that it is much more eaſie to diſcourſe in this manner, then probable to ſee the Effect of ſuch advice. For how is it poſſible that the Proteſtants ſhould ſingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a War againſt <hi>France,</hi> when the Catholicks keep ſuch a ſtrict Watch upon them. We find at this day an apparent example of the Catholick deſigns, by which it is eaſie for us to judge how little Reliance there is upon the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Provinces, where they are reduced to that miſery, that they have more need of our Aſſiſtance. But they had rather the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ſhould periſh, then remit any thing of their Cruelty.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:54547:83"/>
               <p>The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which is maliciouſly incenſed to our Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, does not perceive the heavy Hand of God upon her for ſo many Crimes, for which ſhe is accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his Juſtice in reſpect of us, provoking ſtill the ſame Juſtice by new tranſgreſſions, in contempt of Heavenly Mercy. Nor does ſhe perceive that the Authors of all theſe violent Councels, I mean the Juſuits do not advice theſe things but for their own Intereſt. She is reſolved to ſacrifice the reſt of the Empire to them, as ſhe has already ſacrificed a good part. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs let no man believe that what I have ſaid proceeds from any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Averſion to them, ſo natural to thoſe of my Religion. I proteſt before God, that I bear malice to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:54547:83"/> no Man; and that I would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to them the leaſt of our Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but that I find that none of the honeſt and moderate party of their Religion, have any greater affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them than my ſelf. 'Tis well known that it was their Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after the Eſtates of theſe four <hi>Hungarian</hi> Lords, whoſe <hi>Heads</hi> the Emperor cauſed to be ſtruck off, rather to ſatisfie their urgent <hi>Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities</hi> then for any Crime (unleſs yo will ſay their zeal for their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> was a Crime) that was the main occaſion of <hi>ſheding</hi> their <hi>Blood.</hi> But ſeeing all that I could ſay, would as little prevail as what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſaid before me, it will be better to make an end, and to confeſs that all our Miſeries are at this day reduc'd to ſuch a <hi>Condition,</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:54547:84"/> as well as the <hi>Calamities</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> that our <hi>Preſervation</hi> is only to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from <hi>God</hi> alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="to Poland" type="address">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:54547:84"/>
               <div type="oration">
                  <head>The <hi>Speech</hi> of Monſieur ZIEROW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SKI, the <hi>Emperors</hi> Embaſſador in <hi>Poland.</hi> Spoken in the Royal Palace before his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and in the Preſence of the Princes, Noblemen and Embaſſadors at that Court, at <hi>Tavoravia,</hi> the 6th. of <hi>October, 1682.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Great King,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AMongſt other Books, I have hit upon that of the Life and Exploits of Cardinal <hi>Commendon,</hi> who was ſent to this Court by the Pope, with the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of extraordinary <hi>Legate</hi> in the Empire of <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> and Reign of <hi>Henry de Valois:</hi> I have obſerved in it, that it was that Cardinal's Maxim, Never to anſwer but with an affected Silence and Contempt,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:54547:85"/> to all that his Ememies could do or ſay againſt him. Without doubt, in his Time, the State of Affairs, the Cuſtoms and Spirits were very different from what they now are; at leaſt a long experience has made me judge them very different; and I know I cannot, without great diſadvantage, conceal or connive at a thing that very much troubles me. I have underſtood that the French King's Miniſter's, publiſhed ſome days ago certain Letters, which brought, as it were, aſſured Teſtimonies, that His Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Envoyes only Buſineſs, with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court, was to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by all poſſible means, to turn the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Armies againſt <hi>Poland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no Body but ſees, and your Majeſty muſt needs perceive,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:54547:85"/> how injurious this is to the <hi>Empire;</hi> and to what end it is done. They give this out to diſunite two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; both which, at this preſent Conjuncture of Affairs, have their chief Intereſt in being firmly uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But the Letters took not ſo great an effect as they expected. The Spirits of this Court, were not ſo credulous as to believe them. They are too well ſatisfied in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of the Piety and Affection of thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> to think that the Emperor, my <hi>Maſter,</hi> gives his Embaſſadors ſuch baſe and unworthy Commiſſions. There is no body here that can doubt that his Imperial Majeſty, would be as ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the loſs of <hi>Poland</hi> as of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſince it is as much his Intereſt to preſerve the one as the other.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:54547:86"/>
                  <p>I come not hither, great King, to tell you what through my Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I could publiſh upon little Rumours that have been ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us: I bring your <hi>Majeſty</hi> thoſe things, which I can beyond all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, produce before the whole World, as the true <hi>Originals</hi> of <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>Anſwers,</hi> which the moſt Chriſtian <hi>Kings</hi> Embaſſador, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Du Vernay Boucauld,</hi> who is here preſent, has writ to Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> the Head of the <hi>Malecontents,</hi> or received from him. Theſe will evidently diſcover to your Majeſty, what Affairs Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> has Treated about, with ſo much Secreſie and Circumſpection with <hi>Count Teckeley;</hi> and the reaſon he had ſo cautiouſly to conceal from you, the Commiſſion he had in this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:54547:86"/>
                  <p>I humbly entreat your Majeſty to remember how earneſtly I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated you, to remove the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> from your <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi> as a man pernicious to the <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Poland.</hi> You would have, great King, invincible Proofs and Teſtimonies of what I related; Here they are ſuch as you will wiſh for, and I am perſwaded they will be ſufficient to make you judge the ſpeedy departure of Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> out of your Kingdom, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary. But I fear, troubling your Majeſty with a long <hi>Diſcourſe;</hi> I paſs by a thouſand things which I could add; this Memorial is enough: To you I preſent it with all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable reſpect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="memorial" type="oration">
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:54547:87"/>
                  <head>A <hi>Memorial</hi> preſented to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> by Monſieur <hi>Zierowsky, the</hi> Emperor's Reſident. Which was read in the Preſence of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and before the Princes and Miniſters of his Court; at <hi>Tavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> the 6th. of <hi>October, 1682.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SInce the lact <hi>Memorial,</hi> which I had the Honour to preſent to your Majeſty, I have endeavoured, according to the Advice of the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Lords of the Senate, to furniſh my ſelf with ſome piece that might evidently appear what Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence the <hi>French</hi> King's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents have in your Kingdom with Count <hi>Tekeley,</hi> Head of the <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents</hi> in <hi>Hungary.</hi> Theſe want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo to inform you, what Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:54547:87"/> and Agreements paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which, as I ſaid, tend to the breaking off the Peace and Treaties, that are between your Majeſty and the Emperor, my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. You could not eaſily be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of it, from any but my ſelf. I know the <hi>French</hi> King's Miniſters daily aſſured your Majeſty, that they had a hand in no ſuch thing; and that we accuſed them falſely. And the <hi>French</hi> would no longer be ſuſpected to have any ill <hi>Deſign</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Empire,</hi> after the <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King had made, at the raiſing the <hi>Bloccade</hi> of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh.</hi> His moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty would inform all <hi>Europe,</hi> how he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf in that occaſion; and they were careful to carry his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to all the Courts of the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:54547:88"/> chief <hi>Chriſtian Princes.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King plauſibly declares, that having been informed of the Deſigns which are carrying on in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> againſt the <hi>Empire,</hi> he would put nothing in execution which might hinder his <hi>Imperial Majeſty,</hi> and the moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> from oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Turk</hi> with all their Forces, and providing for the common good of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This could by no means allow your <hi>Majeſty</hi> to believe, that the <hi>French</hi> were in League with the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> and <hi>Turks;</hi> and that they contributed to the taking and plundering the Towns of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> for that appeared to be quite contrary to ſuch fair <hi>Declarations;</hi> but God the Defender and Reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> has ordered thoſe
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:54547:88"/> things to fall into my hands, which I lay at the foot of your Majeſties Throne; and which I lay before the Eyes of the whole <hi>World.</hi> Theſe are the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi>'s Letters, and Correſpondence with Count <hi>Tekeley;</hi> which you will find dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically oppoſite to thoſe Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ſo worthy the piety and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity of the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have made uſe of no evil pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice for the obtaining theſe <hi>Letters:</hi> I have not, though I could have done it, ſo much as employed any Body to obſerve the <hi>French.</hi> And to tell you all, I got theſe Letters by the means of the Steward of the moſt Illuſtrious Lord <hi>Stadnick</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. The Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> after having long importuned the <hi>Monks</hi> of a Monaſtry of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> went
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:54547:89"/> alſo to importune the Steward, who is <hi>Caſtellan</hi> at <hi>Premiſlaw.</hi> So much he did, that he ſtirred up the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans anger againſt himſelf, and ſo conſequently he became my friend, and has ever ſince been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry favourable to my Intentions. This <hi>Castellan,</hi> ſome days ago, ſtopt certain <hi>Hungarians</hi> coming back from <hi>Nimiravia,</hi> whither they went to ſee the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he ordered them to be brought to me, with the Letters he found about them. I preſently took care to convey them to the <hi>Emperor</hi> my Maſter's <hi>Territories;</hi> ſending at the ſame time the Letters, to the end that all the World might judg, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I had not juſt <hi>Cauſe</hi> to ſuſpect, that the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> exceeded his <hi>Masters</hi> Orders.</p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:54547:89"/>
                  <p>Certainly, this Agent, this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, this <hi>Spy,</hi> this <hi>Embaſſador,</hi> I know not what to call him, but I mean Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> has committed a great Outrage againſt all <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Againſt the <hi>Emperor,</hi> in fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and contriving what he has a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Againſt your Majeſty, in entertaining a <hi>Commerce</hi> ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, ſo pernicious, and for ſo long a time, without your knowledg, and in your Kingdom, as if he had been at home. I muſt add, for the Intereſt of your Kingdom; that this <hi>Conduct</hi> has given the <hi>World</hi> occaſion to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> were blind enough, not to ſee the dangers their Neighbours made them fear, and that they would themſelves drive the <hi>Ponyard</hi> to their own Breaſt, in permitting the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:54547:90"/> live amongſt them. His <hi>Proceeding</hi> will, without doubt, appear very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the <hi>French King;</hi> for that Poſterity may judg and believe, that the great King, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV, authorized or commanded, what the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> his <hi>Agent</hi> did in his Name.</p>
                  <p>Your Majeſty will not take it ill, that we have diſcovered to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies at <hi>Francfort</hi> and <hi>Ratisbone;</hi> the Famous Exploits of the <hi>French,</hi> with the Turks and Rebels of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> in your Kingdom, which for ſo many Ages has been cloſely uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Auguſt Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria;</hi> and has always acknowledged its own Intereſt, to preſerve <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> to the Empire, thinking it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for <hi>Poland</hi> to ſubſiſt if <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> ſhall fall.</p>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:54547:90"/>
                  <p>It is now a year, that the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> travels up and down ſeveral parts of your Majeſties Dominions, on the <hi>Borders</hi> of <hi>Hungary.</hi> He always pretends his Maſters, as if we could ſee that <hi>Dantzick</hi> or <hi>Rogiomont,</hi> which are the Places the <hi>French</hi> come through, were not nearer and more proper to receive what Orders the <hi>French</hi> King would ſend, but he ſtays there to obſerve the nearer, the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Hungary:</hi> It may be alſo, to be in a better condition to give Count <hi>Tekeley Joy,</hi> and to get the reputation with him, of the progreſs the <hi>Turks</hi> by his means, might make in that Country</p>
                  <p>I deſire your Majeſty, That after you have ſeen the <hi>Memorial,</hi> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and after you are convinced of all the Arts the <hi>French</hi> have uſed in
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:54547:91"/> this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> you will be pleaſed to order the Seiur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to depart your Dominions, ſince he abuſes his Employments to the prejudice of all Chriſtendom; and renders himſelf unworthy the protection the Law of Nations allows.</p>
                  <p>You may do ſo much the more juſtly, great King, becauſe the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Church, your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſteems them as Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Perſons, who ſide with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, whether it be carrying them Arms, or treating with them.</p>
                  <p>The Seiur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> has drawn this upon his own head, and if he is puniſhed according to his deſerts the moſt Chriſtian King will baniſh him his Kingdom, for exeeding his <hi>Orders,</hi> &amp; engaging his Maſter's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Reputation. In fine, he has
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:54547:91"/> committed his Vilanies in the <hi>French</hi> King's Name, and broke his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters word; acting in all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>obſervance</hi> of it, which if it ſhould fail in the world, could be no where found but in the Mouth of a King or Prince.</p>
                  <p>I doubt not, great King, but all my preſſing, reiterated and juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, will at laſt take effect. The Alliances and Treaties that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Kingdom and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, require it from your Majeſty. And I alſo, with a moſt profound reſpect, beg to be admitted to the honour of ſome part of your Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="letters">
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:54547:92"/>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>
                           <hi>A</hi> Letter <hi>from Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay, <hi>to Count</hi> Emery Tekeley.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I Received with great joy the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, you did me the honour to write to me, from the Camp before <hi>Filleck,</hi> encloſed in the Pacquets of our Embaſſadors at <hi>Constantinople;</hi> nevertheleſs, <hi>I</hi> was a little ſurprized that you ſhould ſeal them before he had ſeen them. <hi>I</hi> wonder alſo you ſaid nothing about the Siege of <hi>Filleck.</hi> However, <hi>I</hi> doubt not but that place, by this time is in your power. Monſieur <hi>Jaygel, I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, knows by my laſt Letters, that <hi>I</hi> have ſeveral times endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſend him what <hi>I</hi> promiſed and let him have what <hi>I</hi> have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:54547:92"/> but <hi>I</hi> always wanted an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. When you ſend any of your People to me, order them not to come to my Houſe but at night, to the end we may do our buſineſs without any bodies knowledge. But what I moſt earneſtly deſire is, that above all things, they take care not to follow the Road that goes directly from <hi>Tavoravia</hi> to <hi>Nimiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via.</hi> For here are ſeveral Poliſh Gentlemen, who by the moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Order, ſearch, viſit and detain all ſtrangers that paſs. The ſafeſt way in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, that they leave <hi>Premiſlaw</hi> and <hi>Toreſlavia</hi> on the right hand, and follow the Road that leads to <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domiria,</hi> leaſt they be ſeen to enter <hi>Nimirovia,</hi> where I am ſurrounded with Spies. I recommend the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:54547:93"/> to you; and deſire you to ſend them according to their Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by the firſt opportunity. I will take the ſame care in all things you ſhall be pleaſed to command me. I am moſt cordially,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your moſt zealous Servant,</hi> Du Vernay Boucald.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Nimirovia,</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Sept.</hi> the 22d. 1682.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:54547:93"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Superſcription <hi>was thus,</hi>
                     <q>To the moſt Illuſtrious Lord, Count <hi>Emery Tekeley,</hi> Lord of <hi>Keſmark</hi> and <hi>Arve,</hi> General of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Army, that fights for it's Country. </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE <hi>Audience</hi> being ended, His <hi>Majesty</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> ſaid, he was convinced of the <hi>French Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> with the <hi>Male-Contents.</hi> He ſhew'd himſelf very angry that the thing had been conceal'd from him. Next day ſome of the <hi>Chief Officers</hi> of his <hi>Court,</hi> had Orders to go and command the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to depart the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> He ſaid, he would obey his <hi>Majesties Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> but that he earneſtly deſired thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to give him ſome
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:54547:94"/> days, that he might take the <hi>Coach</hi> of <hi>Tranſylvania.</hi> On the other ſide, the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s <hi>Reſident</hi> uſed all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and with great Succeſs; for Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi>'s Letter carrier called <hi>Kelemeschi,</hi> returned to <hi>Nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovia,</hi> before his departure. This <hi>Courier</hi> came with thoſe whom <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keley</hi> ſent to the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> with his <hi>Letters;</hi> and thoſe of his great <hi>Agent</hi> and <hi>Confident Jaygel.</hi> Theſe <hi>Couriers</hi> were ſeized, and the <hi>Letters</hi> they had intercepted, were partly writ in <hi>Cyphers,</hi> which you will here find interpreted.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="179" facs="tcp:54547:94"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>A</hi> Letter <hi>from Count</hi> TECKELEY to Monſieur <hi>Du</hi> VERNAY.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I Doubt not, but you have made much of Monſieur <hi>Valentine Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſani</hi> my Envoy. He has always been faithful to me, and very true to my Intereſt. The Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations you gave him touching the Affairs he communicated with you, will without doubt be of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to him, with the moſt Chriſtian King. I am beholding to you for all you have done for him, and ſhall acknowledg it as occaſion ſerves: It is time I ſhould inform you, of the preſent State of my <hi>Affairs.</hi> After I had taken <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> and entred ſome <hi>Forts</hi> about it; I
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:54547:95"/> went with the <hi>Viſier</hi> of <hi>Budas</hi>'s <hi>Troops,</hi> to attack the <hi>Famous</hi> Fort of <hi>Filleck:</hi> The <hi>Inhabitants</hi> refuſed, at firſt, to put themſelves under my <hi>Protection;</hi> but after a Fortnights Siege, they came to beg <hi>I</hi> would admit them to capitulate; <hi>I</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them what they asked; which was, that the <hi>Garriſon,</hi> and what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>People</hi> there was, ſhould go out, carrying with them as much as they could upon their Backs: Then <hi>I</hi> raiſed the <hi>Fort,</hi> in ſight of the <hi>Imperial Army,</hi> which was hard by in the <hi>Mountains.</hi> As <hi>I</hi> am now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, it is marched away; and having ſacked the Town of <hi>Vieux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſols</hi> and other <hi>Places</hi> retires very ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily. <hi>I</hi> deſign to follow the <hi>Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts,</hi> and drive them far off, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore my <hi>Country</hi> to its former Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:54547:95"/> At length the <hi>Emperor</hi> will be forced to yield by <hi>Force,</hi> what we beg as a <hi>Favour.</hi> Heaven has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerated my <hi>Fortune</hi> indeed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what late; but <hi>I</hi> alſo hope, it will draw on a greater and more ſpeedy Vengeance. Sir, <hi>I</hi> will take care to inform you of all my other <hi>Affairs;</hi> however <hi>I</hi> deſire you always to ſtand my <hi>Friend. I</hi> am</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Sir,</salute>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Always ready to ſerve you,</hi> EMERY TEKELEY.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>At the Camp before</hi> Filleck <date>
                                 <hi>Sept.</hi> 18. 1682.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>The Superſcription was:
<q>
                        <hi>To the Moſt Illuſtrious Lord, Monſieur</hi> Du Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay Boucauld, <hi>Embaſſador Extraordinary from the</hi> French King.</q>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="182" facs="tcp:54547:96"/>
                        <head>A <hi>Letter</hi> from Monſieur <hi>Peter Jaigel,</hi> Governour of <hi>Coſſovia,</hi> To Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Du Vernay.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>LAſt Wedneſday we took and raiſed <hi>Filleck;</hi> where above a <hi>Thouſand Janizaries</hi> were ſlain. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the <hi>Viſier</hi> made all the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians</hi> that were preſent, and were under the Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi>'s Dominion, be brought before our <hi>Illuſtrious Count;</hi> then all the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> being Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, Monſieur <hi>Tekeley</hi> was Proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med King, and confirmed in that Quality by the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> who ſent him from the <hi>Port,</hi> a Hat inſtead of a Crown, with a <hi>Standard</hi> and <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> After the Ceremony, the <hi>Count</hi>
                           <pb n="183" facs="tcp:54547:96"/> very modeſtly refuſed the Title of <hi>King:</hi> He is ſatisfyed with that of Prince Regent of <hi>Hungary:</hi> His <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> are, <hi>Emericus Thokolius Princeps, ac partium Regni Hungariae Dominus,</hi> &amp;c. After this Election, the <hi>Viſier</hi> gave him the beſt Troops, to purſue at the <hi>Head</hi> of the Army, thoſe of the <hi>Imperialiſts. Caprara</hi> having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Mountains, pillaged the Towns, and abandoned the Forts <hi>Vigles</hi> and <hi>Zolian,</hi> and is at laſt retir'd and has taken his way towards <hi>Threnezin.</hi> Sir, we had done ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, but we have not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what you promis'd us, and without that ſupply, we are forced to proceed gently in our buſineſs. Monſieur <hi>Nemeſſani</hi> is gone to treat of Affairs, at the <hi>French King</hi>'s <hi>Court.</hi> He needs your <hi>Inſtructions;</hi> we have
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:54547:97"/> order'd him in all things, to Act to your Honour. We will very ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſend you an Expreſs; I beg of you for God's ſake, make him up as large a Sum as you can. I always remain, as I ought,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Your moſt obliged Servant,</hi> Peter Jaigel.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Gaſſovia,</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Sept.</hi> 22d. 1682.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>The Superſcription was,
<q>
                        <hi>To the most Illustrious Lord, Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay Boucauld, <hi>Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Extraordinary from the French King.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:54547:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>After the <hi>Emperors Reſident</hi> had the ſecond time produced theſe <hi>Letters,</hi> and the <hi>Days</hi> appointed were expired, his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> ſent word to the Marquiſs <hi>de Vitry,</hi> the <hi>French Embaſſador</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> to cauſe the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> immediately to retire, that he was weary of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring daily of his new <hi>Deſigns.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
